<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Praxis medicorum antiqua &amp; nova the ancient and modern practice of physick examined, stated, and compared, the preparation and custody of medicines as it was the primitive custom with the princes and great patrons of physick asserted and proved to be the proper charge and grand duty and every physician successively, the new mode of prescribing and filing recipe's with apothecaries manifested an imprudent invention and pernicious innovation, demonstrated from the treble damage and disadvantages that arise thence to physician, patient and the medical science : with enforcing arguments for a return and general conformity to the primitive practice ... / by E. Maynwaring.</title>
            <author>Maynwaringe, Everard, 1628-1699?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 215KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50451</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">9382751</idno>
  <idno type="VID">42923</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264212057</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1512</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26195</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">09382751</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50451)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42923)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1312:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Praxis medicorum antiqua &amp; nova the ancient and modern practice of physick examined, stated, and compared, the preparation and custody of medicines as it was the primitive custom with the princes and great patrons of physick asserted and proved to be the proper charge and grand duty and every physician successively, the new mode of prescribing and filing recipe's with apothecaries manifested an imprudent invention and pernicious innovation, demonstrated from the treble damage and disadvantages that arise thence to physician, patient and the medical science : with enforcing arguments for a return and general conformity to the primitive practice ... / by E. Maynwaring.</title>
                  <author>Maynwaringe, Everard, 1628-1699?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>107 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M. and are to be sold by T. Archer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Therapeutics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42923:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Praxis Medicorum, ANTIQVA &amp; NOVA:</hi> THE Ancient and Modern Practice OF PHYSICK <hi>Examined, Stated, and Compared.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Preparation and Custody of Medicines, as it was the Primitive Custom with the Princes and great Patrons of Physick, asserted, and proved to be the proper charge, and grand duty of every Physician successively.</p>
            <p>The new mode of Prescribing, and Filing <hi>Recipe's</hi> with Apothecaries, manifested an imprudent invention, and pernicious innovation.</p>
            <p>Demonstrated from the treble Damage and Disad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages that arise thence; to Physician, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, and the Medical Science.</p>
            <p>With enforcing Arguments for a return, and general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the Primitive Practice.</p>
            <p>All Objections to the contrary, answered and fully cleared.</p>
            <p>By <hi>E. Maynwaring,</hi> Doctor in Physick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> and are to be sold by <hi>T. Archer</hi> Bookseller, under St. <hi>Dunstan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleetstreet,</hi> 1671.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:42923:2"/>
            <p>Licensed.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>March 17. 1670/1.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42923:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="pages">
            <pb facs="tcp:42923:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42923:3"/>
            <head>The <hi>Ancient</hi> and <hi>Modern</hi> Practice of <hi>PHYSICK, Examined, Stated, and Compared.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT cannot be expected in this small Volume that the whole matter in difference, between the <hi>Ancient</hi> and <hi>modern</hi> Professors in the medicall Science, should be controverted and stated. But that which I aim at, and pitch upon at present to traverse, relates chiefly to the <hi>management</hi> and <hi>mode</hi> of <hi>Practice:</hi> therein to let you understand how differently the affair of <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick</hi> is carried on now of later times, from what it was in former Ages, and from the beginning; lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down and assigning the <hi>benefits</hi> and <hi>advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages</hi> that accrue by the one; as also the <hi>prejudice</hi> and <hi>damages</hi> that arise by the other, necessarily depending thereon, and unavoidable.</p>
            <p>These are the two <hi>cardinal</hi> points, to which this present Discourse is directed, and principally looks at: Yet in the current of this debate, some things else will fall in <hi>parergos,</hi> which we shall animadvert on, as remarkable and to be noted, but not insist thereon at this time. And in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging this <hi>Disceptation,</hi> I must recite and revive some of my own Writings (scattered in several
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42923:4"/> Tracts) that are extant relating to this subject, which I cannot well pass by, but insert in their due places as <hi>valid arguments</hi> not to be smothered and forgotten, but to be preserved in memory so long as the cause in hand remains disputable.</p>
            <p>I must confess, the current of Practice runs strongly against me, by the multitude of <hi>Professors</hi> that are fixed in the contrary course; whose gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral custom and perseverance therein is strongly perswasive to <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Plebeia ingenia magis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplis, auàm or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crob. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. l. 1.</note> inconsiderate, unwary heads, that it is undoubtedly the right way, the most <hi>learned,</hi> and most <hi>advantagious</hi> mode of Practice: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing so great a party appears against me, I am not thereby daunted to oppose their <hi>male</hi>-Practice, though supported by the <hi>authority</hi> and <hi>countenance</hi> of learned men well reputed, exercising therein. And in the designing and carrying on of this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, I would not be misunderstood and deemed a malevolent <hi>detractor,</hi> or <hi>emulator</hi> to any person or party herein concerned; but incited to it by the merits of the cause, and through a just zeal to do a publick service for the sick and infirm, and to promote the honor and improvement of this <hi>Science</hi> I do profess, and now plead for, being at present captivated and ensnared by an abusive Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom, intollerably injurious and destructive.</p>
            <p>I shall not longer detain you with an <hi>Apologeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> premise, but lead you into the substantial matter <hi>indicated</hi> and promised in the front of this Work. And first I will present to your view and consideration, the model and form of the <hi>Primitive Practice,</hi> wherein Physick had its first <hi>Being,</hi> and also increased to a considerable growth, by the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42923:4"/> sole industry of the Professors, without <hi>substitutes</hi> or <hi>subordinate</hi> men, to divide and share with them in their business. After this I shall relate to you the unhappy change and <hi>subversion</hi> of this lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly industrious institution, for the late mode of <hi>Pen Practice,</hi> and <hi>filing Bills</hi> with Apothecaries, generally imitated and followed at this day.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Infancy</hi> of Physick, and during its growth to a considerable improvement; the <hi>learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Professors</hi> thereof, were so careful in their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, and industrious to advance their Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that nothing appertaining to the whole bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness of this Art; but passed through their <hi>own hands,</hi> and was managed under their <hi>own eye;</hi> being privy and present to all concernments; and a faithful Guide in the conduct of the <hi>whole Work:</hi> not refusing the gathering of <hi>Simples,</hi> readily to know, and rightly to distinguish them; examining of <hi>Drugs,</hi> and proving their virtues; <hi>dissecting bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> to view the admirable <hi>systeme</hi> and frame of man; and to understand the <hi>oeconomy</hi> or govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Nature therein: preparing and compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own <hi>Medicines</hi> diligently, to gain a sound and true knowledge in <hi>Pharmacy,</hi> and to be expert in Medicines, and their various <hi>prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> and all this with their <hi>own hands;</hi> and what not? to be truly informed, and ascertained in their Art; and not to depend upon hearsay, or fallacious reports of others, and the insufficiency of such testimonies: deeming it also not fit to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage so <hi>grand</hi> an <hi>Affair,</hi> of which the World was big in expectation, and that so nearly concerns the life of man, by <hi>proxyes</hi> and <hi>substitutes;</hi> but by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42923:5"/> their own <hi>proper labour</hi> and <hi>inspection;</hi> not trust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Herb-women, Apothecaries, and such like.</p>
            <p>This was the <hi>Primitive Practice</hi> of Physicians; and those of the greatest fame and renown, called the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Physicians,</hi> gained that repute and esteem <hi>this way,</hi> by their great labour and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent search into Naturals, for the good of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; refusing no pains that might conduce to the advance of their knowledge. And this was the exemplary, laudable, and constant practice of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sculapius, Hermes Trismegistus, Hippocrates, Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, Caristius, Galen, Scribonius Largus, Andro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machus, Oribasius,</hi> and all the ancient Heroes in Physick: and that it was so, appears by the testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of authentick Writers, as also from their own Works. <hi>Hippocrates</hi> in his Book <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the seventh and eighth Sections, reckons up the accommodation that belongs to a Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, of which he ought not to be destitute; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst which are <hi>Chirurgical instruments</hi> and <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines</hi> of all sorts, that he ought always to have ready in his own keeping; and this he saith will make a Physician more confident in his Practice, and more readily applying himself to the sick, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> so he concludes the eighth Section of that Book.</p>
            <p>Famous <hi>Quercitan</hi> upon this question, <hi>an medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum deceat</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? affirms that the Ancients were very industrious and diligent in the <hi>Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of their Medicines, which they kept in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness by them to serve their Practice. <note n="‖" place="margin">Querce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv. pag. 218.</note>
               <hi>Hippocrates ipse eorum faciem conspuisset, qui praeparandorum suorum remediorum scientiam illi detraxissent, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42923:5"/> utique veteres tam vigiles fuerunt custodes, ut ea nequaquam publica facerent omnibus, sed magna cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione sibi asservarent, &amp; filiis ac nepotibus seriatim tandem committerent, ac per manus traderent.</hi> This also is affirmed by <hi>Sennertus,</hi> a judicious, mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, <note place="margin">Sennert. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitut. med. lib. v. pars 3 Sect. 2. cap. 1.</note> and faithful Writer, handling this question, <hi>an medico liceat componere medicamenta?</hi> holds the affirmative, both from the antiquity of the custom, as also the utility and advantage to Patient and Physician: <hi>Neque etiam praeter dignitatem medici esse componere medicamenta, antiqui illi viri pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentissimi, medicique peritissimi satis docuerunt, qui etsi haberent unguentarios, seplasiarios, &amp; id genus hominum, qui fucos, unguenta &amp; similia praecipuè vendebant, ornando potius quam curando corpori utilia, totam tamen medicamentorum compositionem</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sennert. ibid.</note>
               <hi>ipsis non committebant. Ipsi domi suae medicamenta composuerunt, neque sibi dedecori, sed laudi esse duxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, si rei humano generi utilissimae operam impen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derent, neque plus rationis manuum suarum, quam animi haberent: imo ignaviorum potiùs esse videtur, omnia ministris committere, quorum vel avaritiâ, vel improbitate factum est saepius, ut medicamenta praestantissima quae</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>antiqui appellant, vel indoctissimis empyricis communicarentur, vel cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupta &amp; vitiata authoritatem suam amitterent, nec vires, ob quas ab antiquis praedicabantur, haberent.</hi> You see plainly the judgment of this grave Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the case, that the <hi>preparation</hi> of Medicines by Physicians is as <hi>profitable</hi> and <hi>necessary</hi> as <hi>ancient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as the <hi>preparation</hi> of Medicines was the <hi>general</hi> custom among the ancient Physicians; so likewise that laudable practice hath been continued
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42923:6"/> in all Ages by some of the most <hi>eminent</hi> and most <hi>industrious</hi> Physicians, even since the time <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries</hi> have been in use; such were <hi>Paracelsus, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bavius, Angelus Sala, Basilius Valentinus, Crol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, Quercitan, Mylius, Mynsicht, Faber, Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Schroder, Sennertus, Van Helmont, Glauber, Swelfer, &amp;c.</hi> many more, the most eminent of their times and places where they lived, have been industrious <hi>operators</hi> in <hi>Pharmacy,</hi> whose Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplars are committed to us, to revise, meliorate, and improve.</p>
            <p>The necessity for continuation of this Practice, and incouraging a <hi>general conformity</hi> thereto, will evidently appear to all rational people, if they consider the <hi>enforcements</hi> to it, arising from the whole <hi>interest</hi> and concerns of this <hi>Art,</hi> which are reducible to, or comprised under these 3 heads.</p>
            <p>First, The <hi>improvement</hi> and <hi>advance</hi> of the <hi>Art</hi> it self.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>security</hi> and <hi>utility</hi> to the <hi>Sick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The <hi>advantages</hi> and <hi>satisfaction</hi> to the <hi>Professors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We shall proceed distinctly upon these three <hi>capital</hi> parts, in the order as they stand. And first, that the <hi>Pharmacopaeian</hi> Practice of Physicians is the direct and only way to improve and draw neer to the perfection and compleating of the <hi>Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centic Art;</hi> upon which the whole success of the Medical Science does mainly and chiefly depend; is manifest from the <hi>original</hi> and <hi>primitive</hi> Practice, upon which this <hi>Science</hi> is built and founded: and secondly, from the <hi>successive</hi> and <hi>successful</hi> improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that have been made by <hi>Pharmacopoeian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,</hi> in all Ages to our present times.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:42923:6"/>
            <p>That the origine and invention of Physick did first spring out of an <hi>empyrical</hi> knowledge of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, is confessed by most, if not all Writers, that treat of the <hi>Rise</hi> and <hi>Progress</hi> of Physick: there were no <hi>Principles, Rules,</hi> nor <hi>Method</hi> establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but every one followed the dictates of his own fancy, to make tryal of this or that, or this with that, for a Medicine; which <hi>experiments</hi> and <hi>try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als</hi> of Medicines of their own <hi>invention</hi> and <hi>facture,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Medicus absol. pag. 10, 11.</note> were recorded and reposited as their greatest se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets: So that <hi>Pharmacy</hi> was the <hi>foundation</hi> of <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick,</hi> and here it took its rise, and herein were Physicians first exercised, before any rules were given: and after the frequent exhibiting and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of <hi>Medicaments</hi> in several cases, and obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations thereupon noted; then the <hi>Art</hi> began to be <hi>modelled</hi> and framed into a <hi>Systeme</hi> of parts ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally composed, which by <hi>additions</hi> and <hi>culture</hi> from learned men through all Ages, hath arrived to this improvement we now see.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scribonius Largus,</hi> an ancient Author of sixteen <note place="margin">Scribonius Larg. de compos. medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentor.</note> hundred years standing, in his Book treating of the composition of Medicines saith; <hi>est enim haec pars medicinae, ut maxime necessaria, ita certè an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquissima, &amp; ob haec</hi> (reckoning their virtues) <hi>primùm celebrata ac illustrata.</hi> And to what we have here asserted agrees <hi>Joan. Langius</hi> in his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical <note place="margin">Joan. Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius, Epist. med. lib. 1. Epist. 51.</note> Epistles, a grave Author, conversant with antique Writings: <hi>Scis nempe principium omnium artium esse rude: at temporis successu &amp; experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia adaugeri, &amp; excoli; quod certe medicina, omnium mortalium voto expetita, ac toties immutata indicat: hanc ante &amp; sub Trojani belli temporibus
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42923:7"/> Aesculapius &amp; tandem ejus liberi Machaon &amp; Poda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lirius, ac celebris ille Achillis praeceptor Chiron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cor. Cels. lib. 1. in prooem. Plin. lib. 29. cap. 1. Galen. ad Erasistrat.</note>
               <hi>vulnerum medelis &amp; Pharmacia se exercebant, solis{que} his duabus partibus, nempe Chirurgia &amp; Pharmacia, tum medicina constabat:</hi> and for this he quotes the Authors in the Margent.</p>
            <p>I need go no farther to prove the <hi>antiquity</hi> of Medicines, nor their Authors to be <hi>Pharmacopoeian Physicians</hi> of the greatest repute, and that Physick was planted upon this foundation, being scarce denied by any. I now come to prove the necessity of continuing this Practice, in order to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement and advance of Physick, whereby chiefly the Art is truly enabled to do great things, and adorned with real performances in curing. So far is any <hi>Art</hi> or <hi>Science</hi> improved, by how much more it draws neer and acquires the end, for which it is intended and instituted; the regaining of health is that mark to which all Medicines are ultimately directed: now by the prudent election and exquisite preparation of Medicines is this end attained more especially, and sometimes indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, without the contribution and assistance of the other parts of this Art. For the more distinct and clearer proof of this point I am now upon, I shall lay down these three following <hi>Positions,</hi> of a just latitude, which comprise the full scope of our matter; and which being proved, the first head of our <hi>triple division</hi> stands as a manifest truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Pharmacy or the dextrous preparation of</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Position </seg>1</label>
               <hi>Medicines, is the most excellent and necessary part of Physick; and the main stress of curing,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42923:7"/> lies chiefly in the compleat medicinal appara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That true skill in Pharmacy, and a certain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Position </seg>2</label>
               <hi>of Medicines, is not gained by reading, but by manual preparations and tryals; personally ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving through the whole process of the Medicine, and noting all the circumstances appertaining to it, or casually emerging; whether successful or not; for a future guide, to direct and improve the next process, for the same Medicine; or to admonish, instruct, or caution in another, affine or analogous thereto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the preparation of Medicines is the proper</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Position </seg>3</label>
               <hi>and special business of every Physician; without which experience and certain knowledge in Medicines, he cannot be compleat in his Profession, but very insuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in the grand and most weighty part of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical Science.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To illustrate and prove the verity of first <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Proof </seg>1</label>
               <hi>Thesis,</hi> I proceed thus: The excellency of <hi>Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> and its super-excellency above the other parts of Physick (I mean <hi>Chymical Pharmacy</hi> chiefly) does appear; first, because it is the ground work and foundation of the rest, and it lays open the <hi>mysteries</hi> of the whole <hi>Science,</hi> and gives light to every part thereof. A compleat knowledge here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in does discover the secret operations of Nature, whereby Diseases are more easily detected, and the manner of Curing more obvious and plain. <hi>Ʋbi definit Physicus, ibi incipit Medicus.</hi> Solid knowledge in Natural Philosophy, is the most necessary qualification, preparatory to make a good <hi>Physician:</hi> now this <hi>Philosophy</hi> must be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimental, solid, and certain: the <hi>notional Theorems</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:42923:8"/> in <hi>Philosophy,</hi> the World hath too long insisted on, and spent much time to little purpose, in vain <hi>ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinations, speculative conjectures,</hi> and <hi>verbal proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> And as Natural <hi>Phrlosophy</hi> is <hi>praevious,</hi> and a sit qualification to ground a Physician on in a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral knowledge of Nature, and this knowledge is gained by <hi>experiments</hi> and <hi>mechanick tryals;</hi> so likewise the knowledge of the <hi>microcosme</hi> in a <hi>sound</hi> and <hi>morbid</hi> state, is acquired and discover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and the ways and manner of curing unfolded and directed; by observing <hi>artificial</hi> operations and <hi>mechanical</hi> tryals, which imitate Nature in her perfect and deficient actings: And upon this consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration <hi>Zwelfer</hi> affirms, <note n="*" place="margin">Mantiss. Hermet. praefat.</note>
               <hi>Chymiam esse artem nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lissimam, &amp; medico scitu summè necessariam, &amp; includere universam Philosophiam practicam.</hi> And <hi>Sennertus</hi> treating of <hi>Chymical Pharmacy</hi> brings in <note place="margin">Sennert. de confems. &amp; diss. Chym. cum Galen. cap. 2.</note>
               <hi>Mesues</hi> to speak his thoughts, and to confirm his own opinion: <hi>Ʋt jam de eo nihil dicam quantum in naturae obscuritate investiganda Philosopho lucis praese<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat Chymia: unde rectè à Mesue in Antidotar. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct. 21. cap. de olco ovorum. Chymici appellan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur qui quae occulta sunt in rebus, manifestant &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegunt: Ʋt confidenter dicere ausim, vix aliquem ad peritiorem rerum naturalium cognitionem pervenire posse, qui in Chymicis operationibus, quibus res na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turales artificiosè resolvuntur, &amp; quarum beneficio mirandi rerum consensus &amp; dissensus, ac omnino plurimi effectus aliàs occulti deprehenduntur, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cittus non est.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregor. Horstius</hi> also, and other eminent Writers (though adhering sufficiently and too much to <hi>Calenick</hi> Doctrine) yet will have an exact know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42923:8"/> of <hi>Chymical Pharmacy</hi> so necessary to the compleating a <hi>Physician,</hi> that without it he is of no <note place="margin">Greg. Horst. lib. 10. de Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceuticis.</note> account: <hi>Encomia Chymiae non opus est ut hîc re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>censeam, quia verum est, quod habet alicubi Heurni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us: cespitat jam profectò sine hac arte medicina; quam ob causam rectè dicit P. And. Mathiolus in Epist. Ausim dicere, neminem medicum absolutum esse posse, imò nec mediocrem quidem, qui in hac nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lissima distillandi scientia non sit exercitatus.</hi> And <hi>Helmont</hi> that profound <hi>Philosopher</hi> gives his testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony <note place="margin">Helm. Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cop. pag. 371.</note> of <hi>Chymistry</hi> in these words: <hi>praeparat intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectum ad penetrandum occulta naturae, ponitque in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vestigationem in natura vel ulteriorem, quàm aliae scientiae omnes simul; &amp; penetrat usque ad ultimas profunditates veritatis realis.</hi> What is here attest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of <hi>Chymistry</hi> in general, as the only Key to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock Natures Cabinet, serves to prove, and does include <hi>Pharmaceutic</hi> tryals, to be the most neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary and useful means to acquaint a <hi>Physician</hi> with the whole secrets of his Art.</p>
            <p>From hence it is evident, that the constant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise of <hi>Pharmaceutic Experiments,</hi> and diligent practice in the preparation of Medicines, gives a great advantage to a Physician, and is the most excellent <hi>Philosophical</hi> part of the <hi>medical</hi> Science, giving light to all the rest: for hereby not only a knowledge in Medicines is barely gained (though that is great) but a Physician is hereby acquainted with the operations and defects of Nature; is led into the knowledge of Diseases, and is taught how to <hi>adapt</hi> a Medicine aright, and how Nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives help and assistance in several cases of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stress. An exact <hi>perspective</hi> knowledge of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42923:9"/> (gained by <hi>Experiments</hi> and not otherwise) dilates it self and extends farther than the <hi>Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maceutick</hi> or <hi>Mechanick</hi> part of Physick; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a <hi>Pharmacopoeian Physician</hi> is better enabled to give an account of all the operations and deficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Nature in humane bodies, and the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies that answer thereto, and the manner of their performance, than any other person, taught from the various tryals of <hi>Medicinal Preparations,</hi> which not only discover their peculiar Natures in artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial processes, but withall by <hi>analogie</hi> unfold the <hi>latent</hi> operations and mysteries of the <hi>Microcosme.</hi> You cannot design a Medicine rightly, nor aim at any Disease judiciously and certainly, but from the knowledge you have gained in <hi>Pharmacopoie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> operations and tryals of Medicines; for, by <hi>correcting, digesting, fermenting, distilling, sublim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, volating, fixing, &amp;c.</hi> are Diseases known, by these artificial imitations of Nature, and does lay open the mystery of Curing.</p>
            <p>But secondly, the <hi>super-excellency</hi> of Medicines <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Proof </seg>2</label> appears in their immediate approach to and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with the Disease; so that the <hi>stress</hi> of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring lies <hi>principally</hi> and <hi>mainly</hi> here, in the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and efficacy of Medicines, more than in the other learning of a Physician. The <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Physick</hi> is stiled the most excellent of all <hi>Arts,</hi> because of the end it attains and effects (<hi>health</hi>) which is the most excellent and desirable thing. And although the whole <hi>Art</hi> does contribute to this end; yet more <hi>especially, necessarily,</hi> and <hi>immediately,</hi> Medicine does effect this; and this sometimes alone, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the assistance of the other parts of this <hi>Science:</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:42923:9"/> for a good Medicine shall perform much, given by an illiterate hand; but the most <hi>learned</hi> Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian can do but little to the praise and credit of this Art without a good Medicine. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Blasius</hi> a Doctor of <hi>Amsterdam,</hi> speaking of the necessary accomplishments of a Physician, wherein his knowledge ought to consist; he gives the <hi>preheminence</hi> to Medicines, as the most requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site wherein his knowledge must not fail; because the burden and weight of Curing rests here: <hi>maximè tamen omnium mediorum</hi> (medicines) <hi>qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Blasius in Pet. morel. method. Epist. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat. pag. 3.</note>
               <hi>morbus propelli sanitasque restitui citò, tuto at{que} jucundè queat, natura adhibendique ratio. In his enim omnibus, quibuscun{que} Arti huic praestantissimae sese mancipare animus est, qui cum laude aliquando illam tractare desiderant, maximè ut excellant, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primis allaborandum est.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the same purpose, and severely, <hi>Christ. Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius,</hi> a learned Doctor, urgeth the <hi>precedency</hi> of Medicines before all the rest; for as much as the <hi>life</hi> of the Patient, the <hi>credit</hi> of the Art, and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation</hi> of the Physician, chiefly depends here, and is most eminently manifest: <hi>non immeritò au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lang. mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scellan. cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rios. medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, p. 145.</note>
               <hi>Medici omnibus nervis sollicitos se exhibent cirea remediorum sedulò continuatas inventiones &amp; facturas; siquidem non tantummodò venerandam Antiquitatem hîc habeant fideliter praeeuntem, ac Iatro-Chymicorum Coronam hodieque presso pede lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>data hujus vestigia insequentem; verum ipsissima etiam necessitas &amp; conscientiae cultus impensè id in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcet; quum tam aegrotantium vita, quam medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinae gloria ac medentis fama in remediorum dextrè paratorum sinceritate omnino atque certitudine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistat.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:42923:10"/>
            <p>I could <hi>cite</hi> many others of good Authority, whose judgments concur in this point, and do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the same: but what need I summon in <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> to countenance our Doctrine, when <hi>Reason</hi> urgeth so strongly, and proves our assertion so clearly and undeniably.</p>
            <p>Having shewed you the excellency of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, and confirmed their dignity and merit, as the chiefest part of our Art: I come now to make good the second <hi>Thesis:</hi> that true skill, certain knowledge, and improvement of Medicines, is not attained by reading <hi>Authors,</hi> but by prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and <hi>mechanick</hi> tryals. To introduce a belief hereof we have</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu∣ment. </seg>1</label> First, the Pattern and Example of all the <hi>Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents</hi> (as appears <hi>pag.</hi> 3, 4, 5.) who were industrious and laborious to gain the knowledge of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu∣ment. </seg>2</label> Secondly, The <hi>meliorations</hi> and <hi>improvements</hi> of those <hi>antique Medicines,</hi> by our <hi>modern Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macopoeian</hi> Physicians, confirms it farther: for, when Medicines are any ways improved, by bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more <hi>artificial</hi> preparation, it hath been done by some industrious Physicians who were <hi>operators</hi> in Medicines, and such were the <hi>modern Authors</hi> before named in <hi>pag.</hi> 6. hence it appears, that the whole knowledge of Medicines is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here, and springs from this root; <hi>viz.</hi> manual preparations and tryals of making Medicines, and not otherwise. And as there is yet a <hi>Plus ultra,</hi> room enough for greater Discoveries in <hi>Pharmacy;</hi> either by <hi>invention</hi> of new Medicaments, or by <hi>modelling</hi> and improving of the old, which yet
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42923:10"/> deserves correction: there is no other way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress, rational, secure, and certain, but this of preparation and <hi>manual facture,</hi> as did our <hi>Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors,</hi> and is now imitated by the most ingenious, and ablest Professors of this Age: what otherwise is suggested by <hi>putation</hi> or <hi>traditional</hi> Writings, is dubious at best, fallacious oftentimes and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous upon tryal; and therefore not becoming an <hi>Artist,</hi> nor an honest man of so weighty a charge, as life and health, to venture and rely on.</p>
            <p>I might here bring in the <hi>sentiment</hi> of many learned men to this purpose; but to be brief, one shall speak the sense of the rest; and this from a judicious late Writer, a <hi>Collegiate Physician</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> complaining of the unhappy state of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick; offers what I now urge, as the only remedy for redress, and as the most advantagious means to improve the Art: his words are these. <hi>Besides the securing of the Practice of Physick to Physicians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Jonath. Goddard. <hi>A Discourse of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Physick, &amp;c. pag. 34, 35.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>and the preventing its falling into other hands, which is a necessary advantage; there is another of happy consequence and more honorable, which, by this course of Physicians making their own Medicaments, may be attained; that is, a great improvement in the Art it self, hinted before: For when judicious Physi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ians come to be more familiarly acquainted with the materials of Medicaments, and also to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment and observe operations, and processes upon them; especially the more accurate and artificial, as in Chymical Preparations; they will discover the most advantagious ways of preparation, and the most rational proportions in order to composition; and come to contrive and invent new Medicaments,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42923:11"/> exceeding others in their kinds, and improve, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what they can imagine of themselves, before they have entered this way, and what they can ever otherwise attain; as some learned and ingenious Physicians have done.</hi> This is very plain, and fully asserts the truth of our second <hi>Position;</hi> and concurs with other heads of this Tract.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu∣ment. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, The Nature and Reason of the Work it self, requires <hi>autoptical</hi> Experiments, and proofs by <hi>manual facture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No man can attain to a compleat skill in <hi>manual Arts,</hi> but by <hi>manual</hi> operations; <hi>Pharmacy</hi> is a <hi>manual Art,</hi> therefore not acquired but by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent practice in preparation. The force of our argument is obvious to ordinary capacities; being drawn from daily experience in other <hi>manufacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries:</hi> as <hi>Painting, Carving, Writing, Building, Cookery, Engines</hi> of all sorts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where there is a manifest sensible work to be effected and wrought, resulting from some formed or model<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed matter, and remaining after the <hi>Artist</hi> ceaseth to operate; the perfection thereof, or a sufficient knowledge therein, is not acquired by <hi>contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len. de a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim. fac. cap.</hi>
               </note> and Book reading, but by repetition of acts, in the <hi>manual</hi> labour and business of that Work. To what I have alledged, agrees the saying of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> an ancient and famous Master in this Art. And so I pass on to the next considerable assertion: that this <hi>preparation</hi> of Medicines, and the various <hi>experiments</hi> belonging thereto, is the proper work of every Physician.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reason </seg>1</label> The first Reason is drawn from the <hi>Example</hi> and <hi>Custom</hi> of the <hi>Ancients</hi> (whose industrious Practice
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42923:11"/> was so, and proved, <hi>pag.</hi> 3, 4, 5.) to whom we are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged for their labours in setling some foundation for us to tread on; and from which we ought not to depart and separate; unless it be for truths sake, or some necessity urging: which cannot be alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this case.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reason </seg>2</label> The second pleads thus: for as much as the true knowledge of Medicines and improvement of <hi>Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy,</hi> depends upon practice in preparation (as is already proved <hi>pag.</hi> 15, 16.) this knowledge and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement ought to spring from the Physician, and be reposited in him; else he cannot be able to <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, correct,</hi> and <hi>improve</hi> Medicines: consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then, he is very unfit to undertake the Sick; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unskilful to <hi>adapt, order,</hi> and <hi>appoint</hi> Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines; very unable to perform a Cure; his Title and abilities are very <hi>incongruous,</hi> and more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly he deserves the <hi>Character</hi> of an <hi>Empirick</hi> (in the worst sense) than <hi>Doctor Medicinae;</hi> because he is <hi>medicamentorum imperitus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quercetan</hi> urging this duty upon the <hi>Physician,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quercetan. rediviv. pag. 223.</note> severely checks the ignorance of him who is not well exercised and skilful in the Preparation of Medicines: <hi>Quam turpe est medico, sibi doctor is ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulum arrogare, &amp; materiam, qua uti debet, modum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que illius parandae ac administrandae ignorare, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique se à ministris suis superari? an ignoras expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rientiam rerum esse magistram? ergo Pharmacopoei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us eam Callens magister erit, tu verò bruta statua Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrae affigeris.</hi> Construe that your self, for I am ashamed to render it in English. Where would you have the knowledge to be treasured up, but in him that is Master of the <hi>Art:</hi> he that appoints
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42923:12"/> the medicine, ought to know all that belongs to the medicine, both for the <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> of preparation.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Colledge</hi> of <hi>Physicians</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> considering the many inconveniencies that <hi>emerge</hi> from the neglect of medicines, and trusting that business in other hands; have lately voted it <hi>honorable</hi> for a <hi>Physician</hi> to prepare his own medicines: Truly, if also they had voted it <hi>dishonorable</hi> not to do so, they had then <hi>enacted</hi> compleatly: that was well done, this ought not to be long undone. Well then, if it be <hi>honorable</hi> so to do, do you thus <hi>hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably,</hi> and then will you have honor and praise with all knowing men. There can be no greater, nor more acceptable and advantagious service to this <hi>Profession,</hi> than the regaining of it entire to the true owners; and delivering it successively to the Sons of <hi>Art,</hi> as their <hi>inheritance;</hi> which injuriously and absurdly hath been alienated from the <hi>Aescula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian</hi> Family. But <hi>Rome</hi> was not built in a day; <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> great Affairs move slowly: a general <hi>radicated</hi> custom, is not suddenly broken; but there are great presages of a Change.</p>
            <p>In the interim, the preparation of <hi>medicines</hi> now, is not so <hi>scandalous</hi> to a <hi>Doctor</hi> of <hi>Physick</hi> as formerly; who if once taken notice of for a <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiser</hi> with his own medicines, <hi>ipso facto,</hi> he was pronounced a <hi>Quack</hi> or <hi>Empirick;</hi> he that toucht a medicine went in danger of his reputation: but now <hi>aliares est;</hi> the scene is changed; and I expect very justly too, that it will be <hi>cujus contrarium:</hi> for this is a plain truth, he that does not handle medicines is not fit to touch the sick: he comes
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42923:12"/>
               <hi>illotis manibus,</hi> not well prepared and qualified for that undertaking: in plain terms he is <hi>defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent;</hi> and that <hi>deficiency</hi> the greatest a <hi>Physician</hi> can be guilty of. To separate Medicines from the <hi>Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian,</hi> and make <hi>Pharmacy</hi> a distinct business, is to abstract from him the <hi>quintessence</hi> of his knowledge, is to disarm and disable him from relieving the sick; and to <hi>rob</hi> him of the best and most considerable part of his <hi>Art.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If talking learnedly would charm or cure a Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease; then the <hi>Physician</hi> need not so much regard medicines, but leave that for any body to manage. <hi>Sed herbis, non verbis,</hi> 'tis medicine that cures; here then must be the <hi>Physicians</hi> great care, and exquisite skill; which cannot be expected, but from him that operates and prepares medicines: <hi>An majestas &amp; pompa, hellenismus &amp; latinismus medici nomine tenus, non re,</hi>—so <hi>Quercetan</hi> (though him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self a learned man) goes on sharply reproving the <note place="margin">Quercetan. rediviv. pag. 220.</note>
               <hi>vanity</hi> and <hi>insufficiency</hi> of learning dis-junct and separate from the deligent labour and acquired knowledge in the <hi>preparation</hi> of medicines. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less it is a most <hi>absurd deficiency,</hi> for a Physician to be wanting in the true experienced knowledge of medicines: a Physician to be <hi>ignorant</hi> of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, is as absurd and irrational, as a <hi>Master</hi> of a Ship to be ignorant of the <hi>Compass:</hi> he that knows not medicines, is little better than he which knows no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: What! practice at a <hi>venture!</hi> you may as well throw the <hi>Dice,</hi> whether the Patient shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover or not, as give medicine at random: the old Woman is as safe a Practiser as you, that dare give a medicine of you know not what; nor you
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42923:13"/> know not how made; being not privy to the choice of ingredients, nor present at the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>However, though the game goes thus general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet I am glad (<hi>tandem aliquando</hi>) to see that the preparation of Medicines comes to be esteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and adjudged an <hi>honorable</hi> employ, befitting a learned <hi>Doctor</hi> and <hi>Philosopher:</hi> indeed it is so befitting, that he which is not thus employed, is but a <hi>Truant</hi> and a <hi>Loyterer</hi> in the School of Physick; <hi>an verum est? imò verissimum.</hi> Well then, you <hi>Prescriber</hi> in the mode of <hi>male-Practice;</hi> that have accounted it a <hi>dis-honor,</hi> and a Physicians <hi>shame,</hi> derogating from his dignity, to make Medicines; may now for <hi>shame,</hi> come and make them your self: the <hi>shame</hi> now lies at your door; and there it will lye, until the reproach be taken off, by your return to the <hi>primitive,</hi> industrious, and most <hi>rational</hi> Practice, of inspecting and operating in Medicines.</p>
            <p>Doctor <hi>Thompson,</hi> a learned Physician and expert <hi>operator</hi> in Medicines; lays this charge upon <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Thomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons check to Hen. Stubbs. pag. 33.</hi>
               </note> every Professor, and shews the advantages that assurge from thence in these words, <hi>Physicians ought to make their own Medicines, for thereby they shall prepare them with a satisfactory elegance and exactness, improve them to the greater advantage and gradation; understand their vertues more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; administer them with the more discretion, and acquire a far greater confidence of their success; then may he be stiled</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>an officious Physician indeed; otherwise he can deserve no other title than of a meer Trifler in his Function;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42923:13"/> acting</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>carelesly, perfunctorily, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Medicines are the <hi>Physicians</hi> business, and his proper concern, I further prove thus; That which is of the greatest <hi>importance,</hi> and most ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to be exactly done, requires the greatest care, and strictest <hi>curiosity</hi> by the Physician: but medicines are the <hi>grand</hi> and <hi>chiefest</hi> part of a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians business, upon which more <hi>especially</hi> success or frustration does depend: therefore medicine is his proper and personal business most strictly to be regarded. The <hi>major,</hi> or first proposition I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose none will deny; the <hi>minor</hi> or assumption I have proved at large in <hi>pag.</hi> 10, 11, 12, 13. that I need not repeat here, but refer you back to view the proof. <hi>Sennertus</hi> a Writer of great note and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem, incourageth and adhorts Physicians to this duty of <hi>preparing</hi> Medicines for their own Practice, as a work of great merit and desert. <hi>Nec, ut de</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sennert. institut. lib. 5. part. 3. Sect. 2. cap.</note>
               <hi>Jul. Contareno in hoc negotio scribit Horat. Augeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, culpandus est, si pharmacorum compositioni in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbat medicus, sed potius maximis extollendus landibus, ac praeterea honore atque praemio afficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus: Nemo enim rectiùs composuerit medicamenta quàm medicus; utpote qui materiam remediorum, in qua maxima est differentia, agnoscit iis signis, quae alias indoctis vix commodè explicari queunt; &amp; novit quo pacto integris facultatibus utile ab inutili, purum ab impuro secerni possit; quique mixtionis modum, insperatis quandoque morbis necessarium, optimè tenet, quem indoctus Pharmacopoeius vix asse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur.</hi> And in the same Chapter he saith; <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantissimi medici domi suae suis manibus medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42923:14"/> composuerunt, &amp; suis nominibus insignive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt:</hi> Then he brings in <hi>Valeriola,</hi> though seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly against this Practice; yet cannot deny but the best Physicians in <hi>Galen</hi>'s time prepared their great Antidotes themselves, and accounts it the happiness of that Age. Then says <hi>Sennertus; Et</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eodem cap.</note>
               <hi>cur non sit summa felicitas, si ea medicamenta, in quibus vita hominum sita est, ipsi etiam medici com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponant, nec omnia non rarò indoctis hominibus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittendum.</hi> This Author (much approved and followed) declares himself very plainly for our present purpose: and indeed most Physicians now are sensible of the error they are fallen into, by being snared and carried away with the common <hi>prescribing custom;</hi> and what disadvantages and abuses it hath brought upon this Profession: but such as are riveted in that Practice by <hi>combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> with <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> and enticed away with the <hi>profit</hi> and <hi>ease</hi> of it, are loth to be rousted out; and they can be contented to smother and wink at all the injuries I can reckon up, to <hi>Physician, Patient,</hi> and the <hi>Art</hi> it self: so long as it goes well with them, so long as money comes in freely and easily this way, what care they; what need they trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themselves about medicines: but those who desire sincerely to discharge their duty towards the <hi>sick;</hi> to advance the reputation of this <hi>Science,</hi> and exercise their Profession <hi>knowingly,</hi> and <hi>conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciously,</hi> will have special regard to the medicine, in the election and choice of ingredients; will <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonally</hi> be at the <hi>Preparation;</hi> give out the medicine with due <hi>cautions;</hi> and not commit this, the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiest part of his business, to other men and their Servants.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:42923:14"/>
            <p>I think it much more necessary, that a <hi>Physician</hi> look into the <hi>medicine,</hi> than the <hi>Chamber-Pot</hi> or <hi>Close-Stool,</hi> as a matter of greater concernment; and he shall practice with less <hi>hazard</hi> to his own reputation, and more <hi>security</hi> to his patients life. And I must say, an <hi>error, mistake,</hi> or <hi>abuse</hi> in the medicine, is far greater and more dangerous than a deficiency or error of the Physician in his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Patients Disease:</hi> For, a good medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine is not so tied up and restrained to one disease, but it shall operate for good in many others; so that if a Physician do not so exactly determine aright concerning the <hi>Patients Case;</hi> yet if the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stemper he imagines have but an <hi>affinity,</hi> or some <hi>proportion</hi> with that which really afflicts the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and he gives a proper good medicine accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his own <hi>determination;</hi> this medicine shall succeed well and prevail: but an <hi>adulterate</hi> bad medicine, though adapted and appointed by the most skilful head and deliberate consultation, shall take no <hi>effect,</hi> for the purpose intended, or else have <hi>bad effects.</hi> And therefore I may confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirm, that a Physician of <hi>ordinary</hi> Parts, with <hi>extraordinary</hi> curious medicines, of his own <hi>Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> well tryed and proved, shall perform more and greater <hi>Cures,</hi> and have less <hi>miscarriages,</hi> than the most knowing and learned with <hi>sophisticate,</hi> and ordinary <hi>Shop</hi> medicines, of which no man can have confidence but a presumption. All the curious knowledge that can be comprised in one man or many, cannot cure without good efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous medicines; cannot command a bad medicine from doing mischief; therefore good medicine is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42923:15"/> most to be esteemed, and nicely to be lookt after, as the most excellent and most serviceable part of this <hi>Art;</hi> and the Physicians <hi>personal</hi> business, his <hi>grand</hi> and peculiar concern.</p>
            <p>I see no reason, but that a Physician may as well depend upon the <hi>Chyrurgions</hi> skill in <hi>Anatomy,</hi> as the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> skill in medicines; and lay aside that trouble of dissecting, as well as this of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring medicines: why you should be so much concerned for <hi>Anatomy,</hi> and so little regard medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, the reason does not appear to me, nor is there any thing to be produced: this I am sure, that a good medicine without an exact <hi>anatomical</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, will perform its work; but the greatest skill in <hi>Anatomy,</hi> will not make amends for a frivolous or bad medicine. A <hi>competent</hi> knowledge in <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy,</hi> and an <hi>expert accurate</hi> judgment in medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal preparations, makes an able good Physician; and with this man you may freely and safely trust your life: but if he be the best and most compleat <hi>Anatomist</hi> in the world, having spent much of his time to gain repute in that curiosity, and neglected medicines; save only a <hi>speculative traditional</hi> knowledge, and what he hath gained by <hi>Books</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; he may talk finely, but he can do little; he may get esteem with some kind of people, by his <hi>words</hi> and <hi>terms</hi> of Art, but not by his <hi>works; Cures</hi> will not fame him; he is an uncertain and a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous Practiser; subject to miscarriages and great errors in his undertakings: yet I would not have any think hereby, that I slight <hi>Anatomical</hi> disquisition and knowledge, but I blame the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring of this before the other; the insisting too
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42923:15"/> much upon <hi>Anatomy,</hi> and neglecting <hi>Pharmacy,</hi> which is chief, and gives the main <hi>stroke</hi> in Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</p>
            <p>And for as much as the <hi>mystery</hi> and <hi>dexterity</hi> of Curing, lies <hi>principally</hi> in the <hi>compleat</hi> knowledge of <hi>Pharmacy,</hi> gained by preparation and constant exercise therein (as appears <hi>pag.</hi> 10, 11, 12.) then he that is not a <hi>Pharmacopoeian,</hi> is but <hi>half</hi> a Physician, and the <hi>worst half:</hi> for, the <hi>Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceutick</hi> knowledge excels all the rest, as most <hi>use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> and <hi>safe</hi> in Curing: and if a <hi>Physician</hi> may be allowed some grains, or abatement in knowledge, and pass currant; much better it is that he want weight in any <hi>part</hi> of this <hi>Science,</hi> than in the <hi>Pharmaceutick;</hi> this being the greatest requisite to <hi>constitute</hi> a good Physician, and render him most serviceable to the Sick; and so <hi>necessary,</hi> that without it his seeming abilities are a <hi>meer imposture,</hi> and he undertakes at a venture.</p>
            <p>Hence it plainly and undeniably appears, by what we have said and proved; that not to be <hi>skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> and <hi>expert</hi> in the <hi>manual preparation</hi> of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, is a <hi>great</hi> and <hi>absurd</hi> deficiency in a Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian: not to be <hi>privy</hi> to all that appertains to any Medicine exhibited to the Patient, is a very irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional <hi>custom;</hi> is very dubious and uncertain in the management; is very <hi>dangerous</hi> and oft <hi>pernicious</hi> to the <hi>Sick:</hi> and therefore against all reason it is, that Medicines should be <hi>separated</hi> from the <hi>Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian,</hi> as a distinct charge and business; when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the <hi>Preparation</hi> of Medicines is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>main</hi> business, the <hi>chief</hi> office, and <hi>principal</hi> duty of a Physician. And here was his rise, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42923:16"/> it was this work that did first <hi>constitute</hi> and make him a Physician; and here he ought to continue in this <hi>excellent fundamental</hi> employment; trying and searching out the virtues and properties of naturals, in their <hi>simple genuine,</hi> and various <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound</hi> state, by different <hi>preparations</hi> and <hi>tryals,</hi> and divers <hi>probations</hi> in their use of curation: that from hence by <hi>ocular</hi> inspection, and <hi>manual</hi> tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, which daily brings in a <hi>considerable</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of <hi>requisite</hi> and <hi>necessary</hi> knowledge; we may hereby arrive at more certain solid judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, have a more firm assurance and confidence in this our <hi>Art,</hi> than hitherto the most have had, by trusting too much, and relying upon <hi>Books</hi> as perfect Copies, and <hi>Pharmacopoietick</hi> substitutes, sufficient and as a full discharge of that duty; both which are great enemies to the <hi>proficiency</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatment</hi> of our Science. And therefore that <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sician</hi> who departs from the <hi>primitive,</hi> most <hi>rational, certain,</hi> and <hi>improving</hi> practice in the preparation of medicines; for a new <hi>fangle</hi> and <hi>fashion,</hi> of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing to <hi>Apothecaries;</hi> he deserts the most <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophical,</hi> most <hi>necessary,</hi> and <hi>best</hi> part of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession; he degenerates much from a compleat Physician; he goes out of himself, and halts shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in his abilities, being dismembred in the most substantial part; he is but a piece of a Physician, maimed and disabled from doing true service, and exercising his function iudustriously, knowingly, and faithfully as he ought.</p>
            <p>Having urged strongly this duty and charge of Medicines upon the Physician: I will now make some <hi>objections,</hi> the most <hi>plausible</hi> and seemingly
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42923:16"/>
               <hi>valid</hi> that can be pleaded against it, in the behalf of those that would be exempt from the exercise of this part of their <hi>Profession</hi> and desire to live at ease.</p>
            <p>To excuse the <hi>Physician</hi> from the business of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, and to free him from that trouble, it may be pleaded, <hi>Huic operi non vacat;</hi> he hath not <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> time and leisure from visiting and being visited, to attend the <hi>Preparation</hi> of Medicines, making choice of the best <hi>Drugs,</hi> and what else belongs to this business.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answer. </seg>
               </label> To this I answer: First, no Physician ought to take more business upon him, than what he can discharge <hi>carefully, safely,</hi> and <hi>honestly;</hi> not trust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and relying upon <hi>assistants</hi> (in the principal part) that may hazard and frustrate the whole suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess of his undertaking.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, if a Physician's Practice be so great, he cannot attend the <hi>whole,</hi> but must neglect or fail in some <hi>part</hi> of his duty; then let him fail in the <hi>lesser,</hi> and not in the <hi>main point;</hi> upon which the whole affair does chiefly depend; as it is the case of Medicines already proved. Abate some of your <hi>superfluous visits;</hi> receive an account at <hi>home</hi> sometimes, of the operation of your Medicines, which will give you very good information, how it fares with the Patient, whether better or worse, what hopes, and what <hi>symptome</hi> urgeth most, to occur and obviate next by a secure, efficacious, proper Medicine; and therefore it is much safer for the <hi>Patient,</hi> and the <hi>Physician</hi> shall better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve his <hi>Fee,</hi> to be absent sometimes, in provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good medicines carefully and exactly, than he
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42923:17"/> that often comes to ask the Patient how he does, and leaves the charge of Medicines (the <hi>grand work</hi>) to be managed by another, and his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. Besides, all Diseases are not <hi>acute,</hi> are not so swift in motion, nor suddenly varying with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected and unwonted accidents; but many are <hi>Chronick,</hi> and do not call upon the Physician so quick, and so often, but do give him time and leisure, to attend at his best conveniency.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Patient</hi> thinks, and the <hi>Doctor</hi> would have him believe so; that when he hath visited him, seen his Urine, felt his Pulse, heard his complaints, writ his Bill to the Apothecary; that then help is at hand, great care is taken for his recovery, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be done more or better. Oh, you are much mistaken, the great business is yet to do: the <hi>medicine</hi> which is more considerable, than all the <hi>contents</hi> of this visit, that is referred to the <hi>care</hi> and <hi>skill</hi> of the Apothecary and his Boys. You are more under these hands than the <hi>Doctors;</hi> you are now turned over to the Medicine Makers and Traders; in whose power your life is, and you are liable to suffer for any default, by their <hi>neglect,</hi> want of <hi>skill,</hi> sparing <hi>cost, inadvertency,</hi> and <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight, casualty,</hi> or <hi>haste</hi> of other business, shall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose you: and that from hence Patients do often suffer and miscarry: take the testimony of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Merrett,</hi> a Collegiate Physician of <hi>London,</hi> and a Practiser for 30 years with Apothecaries, <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Merret his short view of the Frauds &amp; Abuses committed by Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries, &amp;c.</note> gives this account of them in his Book lately put forth.</p>
            <p>Pag. 8. <hi>They use Medicines quite contrary to the Prescription, Myrtle leaves for Sena, &amp;c.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42923:17"/> they falsifie the grand compositions of the London Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spensatory, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 9. <hi>'Tis very common for them to load Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines with Honey, and other cheaper ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, and to leave out in whole or in part those of greater value, &amp;c. Such Chymists which sell prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations honestly made, complain that few Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries will go to the price of them. Whence it comes to pass, that most of the Preparations found in the Shops are sophisticated, to the great abuse of City and Country, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 12. <hi>As to their use of decayed Drugs, 'tis so common a practice that I need not give instances of it, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 18. <hi>First, they frequently mistake the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians directions, which of what dangerous conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence it is, every one can tell. Secondly, they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a Medicine appointed for one sick person to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Thirdly, they often neglect the sending of a Medicine in due time, especially such as have no Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, or but raw ones, when the Master is out of Town, or upon long Visits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a Physician seriously considers the <hi>casualties</hi> that attend Medicines, and their uncertainty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not of his own providing; doubtless he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not with <hi>confidence,</hi> nor with an <hi>honest face,</hi> excuse himself from this business, and say, <hi>he hath not time to look after Medicines.</hi> That's a pitiful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable pretence, to say, you have not time to look after Medicines; then, I say, you have not <hi>time</hi> to be <hi>able</hi> and <hi>knowing</hi> in your Profession; then you have not <hi>time</hi> to take a faithful and due <hi>care</hi> over the sick: then you have not <hi>time</hi> to be
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42923:18"/> an <hi>honest</hi> Physician, and you are but a slight and a hazardous undertaker in this weighty affair: you can find time enough to make visits for the <hi>Fees</hi> sake; but you cannot spare <hi>time</hi> to perform your <hi>whole duty;</hi> nor the principal part of your duty, upon which <hi>curing,</hi> and the <hi>safety</hi> of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient does chiefly depend.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, A Physician being provided with a good <hi>Stock</hi> of Medicines, well designed and proved by frequent use, to answer the general operations that practice will put him upon: <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thartick, Emetic, Diaphoretic, Diuretic, Anodyne,</hi> with some appropriate Medicines to principal parts, <hi>Cephalic, Pulmonic, Cardiac, &amp;c.</hi> he being thus accommodated, shall not be puzled or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbed to appoint sufficient and compleat Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines out of this <hi>apparatus</hi> for all his Patients, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his Practice be great, and have many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his charge.</p>
            <p>Now how this <hi>Stock</hi> of Medicines shall be raised, and how it will be managed and maintained with that <hi>facility</hi> and <hi>readiness,</hi> as not to impede and check a Physicians Practice, appears thus. It is <hi>ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally</hi> supposed, that a Physician upon his first en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into this Profession, does not jump present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into a <hi>full Practice;</hi> but he must stay <hi>some years</hi> for it, perhaps <hi>many;</hi> before business throngs him: during which time he hath then leisure enough, to make his <hi>tryals</hi> in the preparation of Medicines; to be throughly acquainted with the <hi>materia me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dica;</hi> and be raising himself a stock of well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Medicines in the several <hi>operations</hi> of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick; such as his <hi>repeated experiments</hi> in their <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:42923:18"/> and <hi>use,</hi> shall give him full satisfaction and a just confidence to rely on, as his standing Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines for all <hi>emergent</hi> occasions: and his <hi>Repository</hi> being thus compleatly furnished; he is then well prepared, fit and ready for a <hi>great practice:</hi> and this stock of Medicines thus <hi>gradually</hi> and <hi>satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factorily</hi> acquired; shall be maintained and supplied with great ease and delight; supposing he make but one Medicine in a Fortnight, or perhaps a longer time: for the Medicines thus designed by <hi>Physici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> will not be like those of the <hi>Shops</hi> (soon <hi>fading</hi> and <hi>losing</hi> their virtues, that little they have) but such as will preserve themselves (with good keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) many years: no great <hi>bustle</hi> then to manage a full practice, no <hi>Pots</hi> nor <hi>Kettles</hi> upon the fire all day; no <hi>syruping,</hi> no <hi>apozems,</hi> no <hi>Barly waters,</hi> no <hi>Clyster decoctions,</hi> no <hi>pulping</hi> for <hi>electuaries, Lohochs, &amp;c.</hi> none of this dirty work nor hurry upon sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den occasions, that makes a great clutter at the Apothecaries Shop, if practice comes in pretty fast. There is a much better and more curious <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signment</hi> of Medicines, a far <hi>neater</hi> way of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring them; less troublesome, more noble and Philosophical, more delightful, and satisfactory, longer lasting, easily and presently dispensed, appositely serving to the whole Practice of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick, and readily answering all occasions that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent.</p>
            <p>To this purpose, a forementioned Author does <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard's Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scourse of the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Practice of Physick.</note> declare himself; shewing the facility of a Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians managing his whole business: Pag. 28. <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever with judgment peruseth the</hi> London Dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satory, <hi>may soon estimate, to what an Epitome
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42923:19"/> it may be reduced, how many Compositions may be spared, how many ingredients almost in every Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition: and whoever with the like judgment consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and casts up the main intentions and indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that occur in Practice, it will not be hard for him to state the remedies adequate and proper to such intentions as are of greatest importance; and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence to be stored with Preparations and Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions ready made of the choicest materials, to the best advantage for use and Practice, more grateful and effectual, and every way more considerable than the Shop Medicines; as Purges, Cordials, Antidotes, &amp;c. which by judgment and Chymical Art, as the case may require, may be so prepared as to last long, without impairing the virtue by keeping, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be always ready; to be of such form as is convenient to be given, either alone, or with some vehicle; which may easily be had, or prepared by the Patient, or any about him.</hi> And in Page the 30. he farther saith. <hi>And it will not be hard for a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sician, making use only of a Servant or Servants (who shall be no ways capable of discovering his se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, but only fit to kindle fires, tend a Still, or Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, beat at a Mortar, &amp;c.) to oversee and with his own hands prepare and compound what is neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary for himself to do; and by this means, though he be in full Practice, at the expence of a few spare hours, to store himself sufficiently for all his occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, of such great remedies and secrets of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to the same purpose, another late Writer of the Colledge of <hi>London;</hi> urging the Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Medicines upon the Physician, as the only
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42923:19"/> means to redress the abuses that have been befallen this Profession, and chiefly from the Apothecaries, who have betrayed their trust. Pag. 48. of that <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> C. T. <hi>his answer to a Letter concerning the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Physick in</hi> England.</note> Answer he saith: <hi>your</hi> 9<seg rend="sup">th</seg> (reason) <hi>consists of many Parts, but all the difficulties insinuated in it, as to the hazard, and charge a young Physician, at his first entrance to Practice may run, in making a competent provision of Medicines, may be obviated easily enough by what you insinuate your self, of remitting easie things, as common Decoctions, Clysters, Ptysans,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to Patients themselves; which may also upon occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and according to emergent exigencies, be actuated by little quantities of generous and lasting remedies; which no Physician that will attempt the way, that you or I would have, but must always have a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent stock of, readily to supply the Sick with upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion; and I doubt not when you and I meet, but that I shall satisfie you, that some of us have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived</hi> à materia medica, <hi>consisting of generous, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting, and acknowledgedly the most effectual known Medicines; which when the trouble of making them is once over, may be contained in a Cabinet not of the largest size; and by present mixtures, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the occasion, and the help of easily prepared Vehicles, may serve as effectually as any other what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, to cure all the Diseases that infect miserable man; or at least to give him all that relief his condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is capable to receive from Medicines: I cannot therefore think, that having some Medicines made from Shops, renders the way you propose better, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause less troublesome then that of the Antients; for I am one of those that cannot value any trouble, that is indeed really necessary to the acquiring an honest
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42923:20"/> and an honourable purpose;</hi>—And so he goes on worthily to encourage Physicians in this under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of Medicines. Neither was this, or the whole discourse, the single judgment of this Author; but in the front of these Printed Papers, you may read there; that they were made publick at the request of several Members of the Colledge of Physicians, which argues their concurrence and consent here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And in the last Page of those Papers, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares his perseverance, where he saith: <hi>That all the Reasons of the</hi> 17<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
               <hi>Proposition are likewise better complyed with, and all the advantages better acquired by the way of wholly making our own Medicines, and having nothing to do with those men (Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries) who have used us so unkindly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You plainly see here that in what I urge, I am not singular; nor is it so <hi>difficult, unreasonable,</hi> and <hi>unpracticable,</hi> as some may imagine, or would fain perswade to that belief: but as it is most advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious to advance the credit of Physick, and secure it from the many abuses now exposed to, and suffered under; so is it very <hi>facil</hi> and easie to be undertaken: and therefore the <hi>objection</hi> offered, as a <hi>bar</hi> to this laudable and much desired work, proves of no <hi>validity</hi> to discourage the industrious Physician, from this attempt of preparing his own Medicines, as did our <hi>Ancestors</hi> of famous me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> A second <hi>objection</hi> and <hi>discouragement,</hi> to hinder and keep off <hi>Physicians</hi> from managing the business of Medicines may be this: That in regard strange <hi>accidents</hi> do happen sometimes to a Patient upon the exhibiting of a Medicine, which no way caused
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42923:20"/> such effects, but arising otherwise: or if the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine did produce them <hi>per se;</hi> it was from some <hi>mistake, neglect,</hi> or other <hi>fault</hi> of the <hi>Apothecary</hi> or his <hi>Servant,</hi> that prepared the Medicine, not from the <hi>Prescriber:</hi> therefore to justifie the actions of <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians,</hi> and to clear them from any unjust imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or censure, from such unwonted strange <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomes</hi> that may happen, or unexpected sudden death; the <hi>Bills</hi> upon the file are a sufficient testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to aver his innocency, sound judgment and skill, and to take off any such scandal: which had he acted alone, and none privy to the Medicine; he could not so well clear himself, but must lye under the reproach.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answer. </seg>
               </label> This seems to be a fair <hi>pretence</hi> at first sight, to discharge a <hi>Physician</hi> from the undertaking of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines; but look further into it, you will find no <hi>substantial</hi> matter, only a spectrum and shadow of reason, which will vanish into nothing. First, By this suggestion, you comply with me, and insinuate that Medicines is the <hi>grand business</hi> in Curing; which according as that is managed, well or ill, a <hi>Physician</hi> is justified or condemned: if his <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>script</hi> be but innocent, he is acquitted and discharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from any scandal; intimating thereby that Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine is the main and chief, whereon a <hi>Physicians</hi> reputation hangs; which does or undoes all.</p>
            <p>Secondly I say, (and admit Medicines to be the main) that an innocent Medicine does not acquit a Physician, either from <hi>malice</hi> (if you can imagine it) or <hi>ignorance;</hi> but he may do mischiefs enough <hi>intendedly</hi> or <hi>ignorantly,</hi> and the <hi>Medicine</hi> not to be accused <hi>in sua natura,</hi> but <hi>pro re nata;</hi> which none
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:42923:21"/> can fully judge of, but a Physician that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versant with the Sick; and none shall detect him, if he be cunning to palliate, or disguise and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent the case otherwise then <hi>re vera</hi> it was: So that the producing of harmless Medicines off the file, does not clear a Physicians reputation sufficiently (to knowing men in these matters) but he must stand a farther tryal and probation of his judgment, in traversing this matter of Fact. You may as well and easily kill your Patient, with an <hi>innocent, slight, frivolous,</hi> or a <hi>good</hi> Medicine; as with a <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous</hi> and <hi>desperate</hi> Medicine that is more manifest in the effects: Do you think to clear your self from scandal by producing the Bills from the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries files? it was but an innocent Cordial of <hi>aq. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riac. Syr. Caryophill.</hi> &amp;c. such like: it was but a common <hi>Clyster;</hi> it was but <hi>Barly water,</hi> or a <hi>Julip</hi> of stilled waters and syrups: it was but this or that <hi>common Medicine,</hi> which is well known to be safe and harmless. The <hi>vulgar</hi> perhaps may clear you upon this, but the <hi>Judicious</hi> and <hi>knowing</hi> will not acquit you thus: Notwithstanding these innocent Medicines (as you call them, and some may think so) you may do great mischief with them and abuse the Sick; you may be a very dunce and proceed indirectly, ignorantly and sottshly. To give such an <hi>innocent</hi> slight Medicine worth nothing (at least to that purpose) when the Patient stands in need of an <hi>efficacious</hi> Medicine, fully to answer the <hi>Indication</hi> prompting and requiring: To give a <hi>Cordial</hi> when the case indicates a <hi>Purge,</hi> or <hi>è con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra;</hi> to exhibit a <hi>Diuretic,</hi> when the indication prompts am <hi>Emetic,</hi> or <hi>è contra;</hi> to appoint a <hi>Julip</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:42923:21"/> when the case urgeth for a <hi>Diaphoretic:</hi> to give an <hi>Opiate</hi> when the case forbids all <hi>Somniferous</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies: to <hi>Phlebotomise</hi> and exhaust nature, when you should <hi>restore</hi> and <hi>strengthen</hi> with <hi>generous</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Medicines; you are hereby accessory to the <hi>death</hi> or miserable <hi>life</hi> of the Patient, by such im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper absurd courses wherein you can hardly be detected, if a Physicians eye be not over you; and you may do what mischief you please, (if advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage lye in that way) and the medicine not appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently accuse you; and therefore this <hi>filing</hi> of <hi>Bil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> with Apothecaries is not sufficient to clear a Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, and to justifie him in Practice; but he may be culpable grosly, and the medicines not condemn him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In the difficult and weighty under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of a <hi>Prince, Governour,</hi> or other great person of publick and eminent concern, where suspition of <hi>treachery</hi> and perfidious practice may arise; very rare it is that a Physician acts <hi>alone,</hi> but two, three, or more consult and determine the <hi>quid agendum</hi> and <hi>quibus auxiliis;</hi> so that no <hi>defamation</hi> or <hi>suspition</hi> can lye upon a single person, as to the medicine, but all are privy to, and acquainted therewith: but suppose a Physician be <hi>sole Agent,</hi> and have the whole charge committed to him; he may easily free his <hi>private Medicines</hi> from suspicion and unjust scandal; if a part of every medicine given, be se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated in the presence of the standers by, and safely kept by them, to be produced and tryed afterwards upon others; if there should be cause of suspicion by strange accidents that may attend the sickness, or unexpected ill success, that may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the exhibiting of any medicine.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:42923:22"/>
            <p>Fourthly, In the charge of Patients of a lower quality and inferiour concern; better it is, and more safe for the <hi>Doctors reputation,</hi> that he suffer under an unjust censure, sometimes and seldom by igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and unskilful people; then often to suffer from the <hi>Apothecaries default</hi> undetected; which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so may justly be charged upon the <hi>Physician,</hi> being his <hi>substitute</hi> and acting in his place, what the <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sician</hi> ought to have done himself: and it is a well grounded truth, that a Physicians <hi>reputation</hi> lyes more and oftner at hazard by the <hi>deficiency</hi> of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines from the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> management, than otherwise from the rash undeserved censure of the <hi>Patient:</hi> and although we do admit that <hi>Patients</hi> sometimes or their friends, may accuse and asperse a <hi>Physician;</hi> better it is that he suffer innocently, having discharged his Conscience in the full per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of his duty, and managing of medicines carefully himself; than deservedly from his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functory slight undertaking, and committing that grand work to others, which is the ground work and foundation of Curing: Nor are <hi>Physicians</hi> exempt from censure and scandal, although their medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines be recorded with the <hi>Apothecary;</hi> but as often shall suffer an ill report, as those whose practice is entire to themselves, and none privy thereto.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Since of late years <hi>Apothecaries</hi> have <hi>betrayed</hi> their trust; are become such bold intruders and invaders of this <hi>Profession,</hi> setting up themselves and affirming their abilities in this undertaking, vyeing with the learned <hi>Professors</hi> in Practice. It is very rational to assert, that <hi>Physicians</hi> reputation cannot be safe to be trusted in such hands; and a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42923:22"/> great imprudency to expose the success of their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to the will and power of those, that are so unjustly and unworthily become their <hi>Competitors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is this my sense alone, but others very knowing Men in this <hi>Faculty</hi> are very sensible of the same, and have declared it publickly; advising <hi>Physicians</hi> to a more secure way of Practice; that is, by <hi>preparing</hi> and <hi>giving</hi> their own medicines. Dr. <hi>Merret</hi> being well acquainted with the carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages and inclinations of <hi>Apothecaries</hi> towards <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians,</hi> having practised with them for many years, gives them this Character. <hi>As to the Physicians in</hi>
               <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Merrets view of the Frauds &amp; Abuses of Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries, &amp;c.</hi> pag. 19.</note>
               <hi>general, they endeavour to extirpate them, and some have been so bold to say, they hope in few years to see never a Physician in</hi> London, <hi>and to profess they will scramble with them for Practice.</hi> Then he goes on to demonstrate: <hi>First, They have always en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured and aimed at the depression and ruine of the Colledge of Physicians, the only Corporation of that Art in</hi> England, <hi>considering rightly that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression of the Colledge is their interest and rise, and the total subversion of it will make them absolute Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters in Physick, and Physitians their Servants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, They have continually traduced the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and troubled them in Parliaments, at the Council board,</hi> &amp;c. <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Dan. Cox, <hi>A discourse of the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and Abuses of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries in preparing Medicines,</hi> &amp;c. Pag. 13. 14. 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And another member of the Colledge complains of them, and warns Physicians to secure themselves by declining that hazardous way of Practice with Apothecaries; his words are these: <hi>Physicians are subject to suffer from the malice or design of Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries; now although Charity obliges us to think well of all men, till their actions discover them to be bad;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42923:23"/> yet such hath been the demeanour of the Apothecaries towards the Physicians, that they have reason to stand upon their guard, and hazard as little with them as they can,</hi> &amp;c. Then he goes on to shew how they <note place="margin">pag. 68. 69</note> may, and how they have wronged Physicians close<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and slily.</p>
            <p>And a fore-named <hi>Author,</hi> in his serious dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of <hi>Physick,</hi> takes cognizance of the abuse <hi>Physicians</hi> are liable to from <hi>Apothecaries;</hi> and that <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dards <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py condition of Physick.</hi> pag. 41. 42 43.</note> the <hi>Physicians</hi> reputation lyes at their mercy. I shall not recite his words (for brevity sake) but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Reader thither. Now these things being seriously considered, the <hi>filing</hi> of <hi>Bills</hi> with <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries</hi> is not a prudent course to secure a Physici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans reputation; but rather exposeth him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and he hazards his credit every day: and therefore this objection in hand is of no force to keep of, or excuse a Physician from preparing his own medicines.</p>
            <p>A third <hi>Objection</hi> against what I have urged may be this: That the making and selling medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines is too <hi>Mechanick,</hi> and below a <hi>Doctor</hi> to stoop to such an inferiour employ; not becoming him, but proper for an <hi>Apothecary</hi> and Tradesman.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answer </seg>
               </label> I Answer, and do confess that some of our <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors</hi> have been so proud, and I may say shallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brain'd (by what I have heard and seen) as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to and comply with this Objection; and have lookt <hi>superciliously</hi> in scorn, and <hi>elated</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves above those <hi>Physicians</hi> that have managed the business of medicines; and the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> (to bring such <hi>Physicians</hi> under contempt and disesteem) call them <hi>Quacks,</hi> and their Practice <hi>Quacking;</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:42923:23"/> and the vulgar (taking their information from such aspersions as these) have had the most industrious, knowing and choicest <hi>Physicians</hi> in the repute of <hi>Mountebanks</hi> or <hi>Empiricks;</hi> or at best, but <hi>Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> of the lower <hi>Classis</hi> and inferiour rank, that are content with a pedling Practice. But their <hi>vanity, folly,</hi> and <hi>madness,</hi> does evidently appear by what I have said; and farther I have to say; that although such as these men, biassed from right reason, by <hi>pride,</hi> self <hi>interest, ignorance,</hi> and <hi>mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>information;</hi> do disdain the preparation of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines in <hi>Physicians,</hi> as unsutable and improper for them; yet this <hi>Phantastic</hi> opinion is but of late standing; it was not so from the beginning, nor is it so now with the the most judicious, and serious inquisitive Persons. And I pray, who are they now of this opinion, or that would perswade the People into this opinion; as for the <hi>Apothecary</hi> it is his interest so to do, and to vilifie all <hi>Pharmaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paeian Physicians,</hi> because his trade will lessen if such men gain credit and acceptance with the <hi>People:</hi> and in time when <hi>People</hi> can see their advantage, perhaps bring their trade out of use. As for the Men of our own <hi>Profession,</hi> that disswade and draw back from us, to hinder this great work of return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Primitive Practice;</hi> who are they? and what is their ends? a lazy <hi>prescribing Doctor,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps here and there one; such as had rather live in <hi>ignorance</hi> and <hi>ease,</hi> than carefully and industri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously gain a compleat knowledge in their <hi>Art,</hi> and discharge their duty honestly towards the <hi>Sick.</hi> A <hi>Doctor!</hi> do you disdain the <hi>principal</hi> part of your Profession? the <hi>foundation</hi> of your Art,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:42923:24"/> and the <hi>safety</hi> of the <hi>Sick?</hi> who, and what are you? Certainly some great Dunce, or great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here must be great <hi>ignorance,</hi> or notable <hi>knavish confederacy</hi> in the case: to vilifie an able <hi>Operator</hi> in Medicines, to asperse and scandalize an indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious inquirer by <hi>Experiments,</hi> into the nature of all Medicinal Ingredients; a zealous labourer and <hi>prosecutor</hi> after knowledge in the <hi>preparation</hi> of Medicines; a <hi>careful</hi> undertaker of the Sick; a <hi>legitimate</hi> dignifyed Professor that performs his <hi>whole duty,</hi> and bauks at nothing he ought to do; a learned <hi>Philosopher,</hi> more learned and truly knowing then your self. This must needs be gross <hi>ignorance,</hi> or a <hi>crafty knavish</hi> device, to excuse your idle Worship from labour, diligence and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry in the duty of your employment; by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting from the worthiness of other men, and condemning that which is most laudable: rather than you will lose your <hi>ease</hi> and and <hi>gainful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate friendship</hi> with an Apothecary; you will not stick to undervalue the most knowing and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophical part</hi> of this Art, and despise the most learned <hi>exemplary Philosopher</hi> in this faculty. Are you better than <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen, Libavius</hi> and <hi>Helmont?</hi> and all the Ancient and Modern Worthies that have been diligent labourers in <hi>Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maceutic Experiments,</hi> and kept their Medicines in their own <hi>custody,</hi> and dispenced them to their Patients? how comes your <hi>honour</hi> to be infringed by this work more then theirs? and have we it not recorded in many good <hi>Authors</hi> which you own, that <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Emperours</hi> have made Medicines to be satisfied in, and commend the excellent know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:42923:24"/> thereof to the world; and several Medicines are called by their <hi>names,</hi> as the <hi>Inventors</hi> and <hi>Authors</hi> thereof by <hi>preparation?</hi> and do we not know that great <hi>Ladies</hi> in these days do not think it <hi>dishonourable</hi> to busie themselves sometimes in the ordinary making of Medicines? and have we not a more <hi>sublime</hi> way of preparing Medicines, becoming and fit only for a great <hi>Philosopher</hi> and <hi>Doctor</hi> of Physick? oh, but you are a <hi>Doctor</hi> of the <hi>imperial</hi> part of Physick! you scorn the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanic</hi> part; a <hi>Doctor</hi> of the <hi>gentile, easie, talking Practice;</hi> you are a <hi>Pothecary Doctor!</hi> I cry you mercy Sir, I did not take so much notice hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of the <hi>addition</hi> to your <hi>Doctoral Title;</hi> you have climed very high to step into a <hi>Pothecaryes</hi> shop. I hope you will not think your self affront<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor be disgusted, if I should call you a <hi>Journey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Doctor;</hi> much good may you do with your new <hi>honour,</hi> and much good may we have <hi>without it;</hi> proceed on if you think it well, but if we take you by the Ear sometimes, you must bear it pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, for I know not how you will help your self fairly; and justifie your self to be an <hi>honest, able,</hi> and <hi>careful</hi> Practiser.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>servile</hi> works that belongs to Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, that is not the <hi>Doctors</hi> part; he is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to toy in the <hi>drudgery</hi> of it, that is his <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> work; but he must <hi>supervise</hi> and take care <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Medic. absolut.</hi> pag. 92.</note> there be no <hi>neglect, mistake</hi> or <hi>abuse:</hi> he may have <hi>work-men</hi> to do the work, but in the interim he must be <hi>work-master,</hi> to <hi>design</hi> the Medicine, to <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, correct,</hi> and <hi>over-look</hi> the whole business; he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and where the <hi>curiosity,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:42923:25"/> mystery</hi> and <hi>Intrigue</hi> of the Art lies, that is to be done by his own hand, that is his Closet bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quercitan</hi> a great Doctor of <hi>Paris,</hi> very famous <note place="margin">Quercet. <hi>rediviv.</hi> p. 219. 220.</note> in his time, and Physician to the <hi>French King;</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rides the foolish pride of those men that think the preparation of Medicines an inferior work, and derogating from the <hi>Title</hi> of <hi>Doctor:</hi> he rather cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures them as undeserving of that <hi>Title,</hi> that is not <hi>conversant</hi> and very knowing in the making of Medicines. See how he checks those men that scorn the preparation of Medicines. And <hi>Rolfincius</hi> says, <note place="margin">Rolfine. <hi>Chym. in Art. form. redact.</hi> pag. 31.</note> that industry in the preparation of Medicines <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends</hi> a Physician, and adds to his reputation: <hi>Elevat mediri eminentiam &amp; existimationem, si &amp; manum &amp; mentem adhibeat, ipse{que} modum compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendi Selectissima arcana non solum norit, sed &amp;</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 32.</note>
               <hi>eadum praeparet—submissio &amp; humilitas haec pro salute aegrorum suscepta eum neutiquam dedecet, non magis, quam sputorum &amp; urinarum inspectio, sterco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumque exploratio. Senertus</hi> likewise was of the <note place="margin">Sennert. <hi>institut.</hi> lib. 5. part. 3. Sect 2. Cap. 1.</note> same opinion, and exhorts to this work: <hi>Neque preter dignitatem Medici esse, componere Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta, antiqui illi viri prudentissimi, Medici{que} peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tissimi satis docuerunt—ipsi domi suae Medicamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta composuerunt, ne{que} sibi dedecori, se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>audi esse dux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt—</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Antients</hi> who called Medicines <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, did not judge it meet that they should be handled and managed by profane illiterate men; but made Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines their chief business and proper work: and as this was their Practice, so is it now approved by the most knowing men of our Age: and as I told
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:42923:25"/> you before, the <hi>Colledge</hi> of <hi>London</hi> have voted it <hi>honourable</hi> for Physicians to make their own Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines: indeed it is so <hi>honourable</hi> and praise wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, that he which doth it not, cannot be a man of value and worth in the matter of Curing; for he is not an able and safe Practiser, let his parts other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise be ever so great and excellent. That Society claims a great share in the improvement of the Medical Art: this will abundantly be enlarged, and amount to more than all the <hi>rest;</hi> if they restore the Practice of <hi>Physick intire</hi> to the <hi>Prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssors</hi> again, as it was in ancient times. If this <hi>Colledge</hi> be the first <hi>Society</hi> that shakes of the yoke of <hi>Copartnership,</hi> and breaks of that pernicious custom of prescribing to, and filing Bills with <hi>Apothecaries;</hi> doubtless it will be recorded as the most prudent generous <hi>Act,</hi> and most advantagious to the honour and welfare of this <hi>Science,</hi> and an <hi>egregious exemplar</hi> for the whole world to follow; which doubtless will be general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imitated and followed, when an eminent body shall lead the <hi>Van;</hi> as I hope it will be the <hi>honour</hi> of our <hi>Nation,</hi> thus to put formost, and shew a singular zeal to redeem this <hi>excellent Art,</hi> and rescue it out of bondage and insufferable inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; this will be a work so worthy and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that our <hi>posterity</hi> and <hi>Successors</hi> will have an <hi>honourable</hi> mention and <hi>Cordate</hi> esteem for all those who have contributed their endeavours for so happy a <hi>restitution,</hi> and delivering this Art <hi>whole</hi> and <hi>intire</hi> to them; which while the world stands, will never be alienated nor divided again; having had a sufficient <hi>proof</hi> by our recorded <hi>complaints,</hi> of the great <hi>inconveniencies</hi> and <hi>danger</hi> that arise
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42923:26"/> thereby, to the insufferable disadvantages of all industrious <hi>Professors,</hi> and great injuries to the <hi>sick.</hi> This happy <hi>restauration</hi> of <hi>Physick</hi> will be cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated to perpetuity, and this <hi>Annus Redemptionis,</hi> never to be forgotten by all honest Professors in this faculty. In other <hi>parts</hi> of the <hi>world</hi> they are sensible of what we now complain of, and have this matter under <hi>consideration,</hi> and many have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined the <hi>Pen-practice,</hi> and are become industrious <hi>Operators</hi> in <hi>Pharmacy:</hi> As for those that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to get money in a <hi>degenerate</hi> unwarrantable way; <hi>Oportet haberi,</hi> and care not how it come; all is well if it do but come, although ignobly by <hi>craft</hi> and <hi>complices;</hi> they are to be marked, <hi>nigro Carbone,</hi> as being of a <hi>spurious</hi> hatch, and a disgrace to the <hi>Aesculapian</hi> family.</p>
            <p>But although we have evidenced the <hi>Preparation</hi> of Medicines to be a worthy employ, befitting, and properly the Doctors business; yet the selling of these Medicines some may scruple at, as inferiour and too like a <hi>Tradesman.</hi> I need give no other answer to this, then what a <hi>Professor</hi> before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned hath already done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That for a Physician to drive such a trade for its</hi>
               <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Jonath. Goddards <hi>discourse,</hi> &amp;c. pag. 37.</note>
               <hi>own sake, or meerly for profit that might accrue to him thereby, could not be of credit; but in order to so necessary an end, as the securing of his Practice, and the benefit of his own industry to himself; and to so good an end as the improvement of his Art to the benefit of others; it can be no more dishonourable to him to s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Physick, than to persons of honour and great estates, to sell their Corn, Cattel, Wool, or Foreign Princes their Wines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>4</label>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:42923:26"/>A fourth Objection comes in and crys very loud, and seemingly upon just grounds: <hi>That it is a very hard case, a company of men promoted by Physicians, and afterwards established by Law; should by Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians be decryed and set aside as useless, exposing them and their Families to necessity and unwarrantable Practices for their support; and they being increased in number treble within this forty years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answer </seg>
               </label> I answer; <hi>First,</hi> That the imprudent and incau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telous <hi>Act</hi> of our <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>decessors,</hi> in dividing and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating Pharmacy from the <hi>Physicians</hi> care and management (his <hi>chief</hi> and <hi>special</hi> business) is not a <hi>perpetual obligation</hi> upon their Successors, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve and continue the same, against all <hi>inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies</hi> and <hi>prejudices</hi> that shall arise thereby, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unthought of and unprovided against.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>legal establishments</hi> of our Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are not like the Laws of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Persians</hi> unalterble; but according to the constitution of <hi>times</hi> and <hi>occasions,</hi> do admit of <hi>alteration</hi> or <hi>aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> if <hi>Apothecaries</hi> in those days did seem to be a conveniency to <hi>Physicians</hi> and to the <hi>People,</hi> yet by what hath been manifestly proved, the case is altered, and the <hi>inconveniencies</hi> do <hi>preponderate</hi> that little good and advantage that first attended such an establishment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If ruine must fall upon one party; bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more reasonable the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> should suffer, than the <hi>Physicians:</hi> better for the Publick that it fall upon the <hi>Ministerial</hi> than the <hi>Magiste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial</hi> part; the unlearned men than the learned: he that is <hi>Master</hi> of the <hi>Art,</hi> that propagates, increaseth and advanceth it, more fit <hi>he</hi> should be regarded
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:42923:27"/> and preserved, than <hi>he</hi> that is <hi>subvervient</hi> and an <hi>inferior Operator,</hi> that acts by instruction and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment; <hi>huc us{que} deventum est,</hi> the one or the other must decay and grow out of esteem: for if this Art continue long as it is <hi>divided,</hi> between the <hi>Physitian</hi> and the <hi>Apothecary;</hi> this <hi>Agent</hi> in trust, by several sinister ways and advantages, will eat out the <hi>credit</hi> of his <hi>Master;</hi> and you will find the <hi>Professors</hi> to wither away by degrees, and grow less in the opinion of the <hi>People,</hi> as the <hi>other</hi> multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies and gets repute: the <hi>presages</hi> are apparent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and the <hi>Prognostick</hi> very rational: the <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians</hi> support will decrease, being subtracted by their <hi>Agents;</hi> and their esteem will gather <hi>rust</hi> for want of employment, and their parts will be <hi>flat</hi> and <hi>dispirited,</hi> to see such <hi>subordinate inferior</hi> men incroach upon their rights, and act in their place as <hi>Physicians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Since <hi>Apothecaries</hi> have betrayed the trust reposed in them by <hi>Physicians,</hi> which is <hi>essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial</hi> to their being, and the great motive to their constitution; and have <hi>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olted</hi> from that obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of <hi>Physitians</hi> business, regarding more a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>trade</hi> of their <hi>own,</hi> and a <hi>usurped practice</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily stollen from their <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ters</hi> and <hi>Founders:</hi> I judge it most reasonable and the clearest justice, for <hi>Physicians</hi> to <hi>desert</hi> them, and <hi>re-assume</hi> that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness and trust into their own <hi>hands</hi> again; and not to do it, is to be <hi>stupid</hi> and <hi>sensless,</hi> unjust to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, <hi>connivers</hi> at their own and their Patients abuses, <hi>regardless</hi> of the <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>repute</hi> of that Science they profess.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The fafe and speedy <hi>recovery</hi> of the <hi>sick</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:42923:27"/> (the aim and end of Physick) lying principally in the <hi>Physicians care</hi> and <hi>management</hi> of Medicines (as appears through the whole Discourse) this ought and must be preferred, and is of far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter concern, than the profit or maintenance of a <hi>particular company</hi> of men; whose constitution was intended and ordained for the welfare and benefit of <hi>Patient</hi> and <hi>Physician,</hi> in the good provision and secure dispensing of Medicines: but upon long and sad experience, not proving so to either, but much otherwise; there is no valid reason, nor plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible Plea for their continuance, (as appendants to Physicians) contrary to the <hi>publick interest,</hi> the safety and advantage of all the people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Although <hi>Apothecaries</hi> be multiplied in number, to the detriment of some few that would live honestly of their Trades; and puts the most if not all upon sinister ways, <hi>usurping</hi> the Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians right, and <hi>contriving gain</hi> more than the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency</hi> and <hi>faithful provision</hi> of Medicines: yet this inconvenience and pretended necessity is from <hi>themselves;</hi> tolerating so many <hi>Apprentices</hi> to be admitted, which lies in their own power to obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and prevent: but a great occasion of this was, that the <hi>Master</hi> being a <hi>Practiser</hi> in Physick, must have more than one <hi>Apprentice</hi> to make medicines, whilst he is <hi>visiting</hi> his <hi>Patients</hi> abroad, leaving <hi>Physicians Prescripts,</hi> and the Shop Trade to be managed by the <hi>Boys:</hi> So that this <hi>supernumerary</hi> was caused by your <hi>treacherous usurpation</hi> of the Physicians <hi>function;</hi> and improvident neglect of your <hi>future welfare,</hi> in the honest discharge of your <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>trust:</hi> and must the <hi>Physician</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:42923:28"/> suffer, because you have wronged him, and continued it into a <hi>Custom?</hi> and will you alledge that for an argument against his <hi>just relief,</hi> which in his <hi>just complaint</hi> against you?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Although <hi>Physicians</hi> do depart from them, they are not then <hi>left destitute</hi> of a liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; they have a <hi>Shop Trade</hi> to stick to; and <hi>such</hi> a <hi>Trade</hi> as no other hath the <hi>like gain,</hi> nor ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged (<hi>caeteris paribus</hi>) with so <hi>little a stock:</hi> So that there is no such fear they will be <hi>exposed</hi> to <hi>hardship;</hi> and if you consider too, that although <hi>Physicians</hi> do recede from them, they will have <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients,</hi> as well as <hi>Customers</hi> to their Shop, and many people will apply to them: So good an opinion have many people of the <hi>skill</hi> and <hi>honesty</hi> of an <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary,</hi> that you need not fear but he will live, and better perhaps than some <hi>able</hi> and <hi>worthy Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians,</hi> that are very sedulous and industrious to gain a good repute in this Profession, by long <hi>stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> and great <hi>charge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having made enquiry into, and run through the most <hi>material</hi> and <hi>valid objections</hi> that stand in <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position</hi> to our third <hi>Position;</hi> I wave some trifling <note place="margin">Second en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement.</note> ones, and come now to the <hi>second enforcement</hi> of this duty urged upon <hi>Physicians;</hi> and that is drawn from the <hi>benefits</hi> that accrue to the <hi>Sick;</hi> and they are comprised (chiefly) under these two heads; <hi>Security</hi> and <hi>Ʋtility;</hi> which I shall handle di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctly.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Patient</hi> is more <hi>safe,</hi> and free from <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards, abuses,</hi> and <hi>casual accidents</hi> from mistakes or otherwise, under a <hi>Physician</hi> who takes upon him the <hi>management</hi> and <hi>care</hi> of Medicines; than un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:42923:28"/> another (though very learned) who commits that trust into the hands of an <hi>Apothecary</hi> and his Servants; will appear an evident truth if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider.</p>
            <p>First, The <hi>difference</hi> in point of <hi>ability</hi> and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain knowledge between the <hi>Pharmacopoeian,</hi> and the <hi>Prescribing Doctor:</hi> how the <hi>first</hi> excels and surpasseth the <hi>latter:</hi> and there is great reason for it; that a <hi>Physician</hi> constantly practising and pursu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing knowledge in the preparation of Medicines, should be far more able and expert in Medicines; more certainly and securely design them than any <hi>other</hi> (let his learning be ever so great) that directs and prescribes at a probable venture, from the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance of <hi>Books,</hi> and the fallacious reports of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,</hi> that take up upon trust from one another: this is fully proved <hi>pag.</hi> 15, 16, and in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing part of this Discourse.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The great difference between the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines of the <hi>Pharmacopoeian Doctor;</hi> and those of the <hi>Pharmacopoeian Tradesman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In comparing the two <hi>Physicians</hi> together, we prove the <hi>designment</hi> of medicines to be more skill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, certain, and exact; and more knowing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appointed by the <hi>one,</hi> than by the <hi>other.</hi> In comparing with the <hi>Apothecary</hi> we shall evidence that medicines have a better <hi>management,</hi> are more carefully and more honestly made, by the Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian than by him. The reasons perswading and urging to this belief are,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> The incumbency of the charge and sole management, resting upon the <hi>Physician,</hi> rendring him inexcusable in the miscarriage or abuse of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:42923:29"/> does therefore excite him to a <hi>double dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> having no way to evade the guilt, but must take it upon him. We may then reasonably ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that a <hi>Physician</hi> having the whole charge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and what miscarriage happens, or ill suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess issues from any medicine must lie at his door, and be charged upon his account; must therefore have a sedulous care and diligent attention upon the whole affair, must be very <hi>exact</hi> in the <hi>election</hi> of ingredients, their due <hi>weight,</hi> proper <hi>prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and artificial <hi>composition;</hi> since his fame and credit only lies at stake for all; this must needs quicken him and stir him up to the greatest care and nicest observance imaginable. Now if an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary and his Boys (bred up in a <hi>Shop trading</hi> way, and <hi>cursory</hi> managing of business) can be thus <hi>sensible,</hi> and always <hi>cogitative</hi> of this great charge that lies upon them; can be thus scrupulous and exact, in the compleat discharge of this great trust (the failing whereof is often mortal) judge you.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="pages">
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The different <hi>interests</hi> and <hi>aims</hi> of the two Persons (<hi>reputation</hi> in the Physician, <hi>profit</hi> in the Apothecary) argues their prime intentions to be <hi>excentric,</hi> and of a different bias; must there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take several ways, and go by <hi>different medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums</hi> to arrive thither. The <hi>first</hi> runs parallel and even with the Patients safe and speedy recovery; the <hi>latter</hi> moves sinisterly, is biassed and swayed towards the present advantage of the Purse. If it be a mans <hi>interest</hi> and advantage to be <hi>honest</hi> in any undertaking; we may easily believe that man to be honest, because there is no profit to temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him to be otherwise: it is just so with the <hi>Physician</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:42923:29"/> in point of medicines: 'tis not the <hi>price</hi> of a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, that is his gain; but the <hi>fame</hi> and <hi>reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of a medicine, which is excellent in perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great and good effects, that is his great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage and profit: So that profit comes in to him <hi>consecutivè,</hi> and <hi>emerging</hi> as the result of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; <hi>honorably</hi> not <hi>mechanically:</hi> and this profit does not, cannot tempt him to unjust actions, but puts him upon virtuous and most laudable endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to acquire it: and although a <hi>Physician</hi> in other matters were a very dishonest man and used no conscience; yet in this where his <hi>reputation,</hi> his <hi>advancement</hi> and <hi>profit</hi> lies, there he will be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, because his <hi>interest</hi> leads him to it, and there is no <hi>temptation</hi> to be dishonest and falsifie his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines; nothing but <hi>perfect folly,</hi> and acting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst himself, can make a <hi>Physician</hi> be unfaithful or careless in medicines. Is not he a mad man, that to get a crown or ten shillings more, by abusing and sophisticating three or four medicines, shall thereby lose the advantage of a <hi>Cure,</hi> lose his <hi>reputation,</hi> lose the good <hi>opinion</hi> of his Patient, his relations and acquaintance, that would have brought <hi>pounds</hi> to him: so that instead of <hi>gaining</hi> by the cheat, he is a great <hi>loser;</hi> and no man (I think) in his wits will cheat for loss, though many do for gain.</p>
            <p>The case is not thus with the <hi>Tradesman</hi> in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick: it is with him as it is with other <hi>Shop men:</hi> a Tradesman reckons his profit, by what his Ware <hi>cost,</hi> and what he <hi>sells</hi> it for; so much more as he gets in the <hi>selling,</hi> so much profit he accounts to his <hi>Purse:</hi> and therefore <hi>Tradesmen</hi> when they buy, chuse such <hi>Commodities</hi> as they can get most by in
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:42923:30"/> retailing: and do you think it is not so in the <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine trade?</hi> of necessity it must be so, if you consider, that all the <hi>Drugs</hi> imported into <hi>England,</hi> sooner or later, they are <hi>sold</hi> and made into <hi>medicine,</hi> although they have lain by <hi>years,</hi> with the <hi>Merchant, Druggist</hi> and <hi>Apothecary,</hi> before they are used: now look upon the <hi>Drugs,</hi> and you shall see <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three</hi> sorts and degrees of each of them in point of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness: one sort is <hi>fine ware</hi> and <hi>choice;</hi> another sort is <hi>course</hi> and <hi>degenerate,</hi> perhaps of the growth of another <hi>Country</hi> not so good; a <hi>third</hi> is damnified and decayed by <hi>transportation</hi> or <hi>long keeping.</hi> Now for these several sorts of the same <hi>species</hi> or kind; as they differ in <hi>goodness,</hi> so you have <hi>several prices</hi> set you: and you shall have one, for 20 <hi>s.</hi> the pound, the other for 30 <hi>s.</hi> the best 40 <hi>s.</hi> or perhaps 50. Now if there be such difference (as certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there is) in Drugs both for <hi>price</hi> and <hi>goodness;</hi> then we may conclude, that there is as much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the <hi>goodness</hi> of <hi>medicines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what becomes of these three sorts of Drugs? <hi>first</hi> or <hi>last,</hi> they are all sold, <hi>good</hi> and <hi>bad,</hi> all is turned into Medicine. The <hi>Pharmacopoeian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> that prepares Medicines for his own Practice; he is so <hi>nice</hi> and <hi>curious</hi> in the choice of his Drugs, that none but the very best will go down with him, he defies the <hi>degenerate</hi> and <hi>decayed sort,</hi> he stands not upon the <hi>price,</hi> that shall not make him refuse the Commodity; and it is his interest and best policy so to do, because he lives and thrives by <hi>Cures,</hi> not by <hi>selling</hi> of <hi>Medicines.</hi> And I have heard some <hi>Druggists</hi> say, if all their Customers were so curious to pick out the choicest of their
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:42923:30"/> ware and leave the other, they knew not how to manage their Trade, and live by it. What then becomes of the <hi>trash</hi> and <hi>courser</hi> sort? there are <hi>Chapmen</hi> for that too; there are those that drive a <hi>Trade</hi> in Physick; and <hi>Tradesmen</hi> will not give <hi>forty shillings,</hi> if they can buy for <hi>twenty;</hi> especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when a Commodity may be sold again without <hi>discovery</hi> of its badness. And such is the case of Drugs, when they are <hi>compounded</hi> and converted into medicine, they are not discernable, but pass currant. Now ask your own reason, if it be not more safe, and may you not have more confidence in medicines from the <hi>Physicians</hi> hand, than from <hi>another,</hi> that makes a <hi>Trade</hi> of Physick; especially in this Age, when there is so much fraud and deceit in <hi>buying</hi> and <hi>selling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Shop Medicines</hi> are commonly thus abused <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Merrets <hi>View of the frauds and abuses com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, &amp;c. p 8. 9. 10. 11. 12. 13.</hi>
               </note> and falsified, see what a Practiser with <hi>Apothecaries</hi> for 30 years in this City saith; <hi>Doctor Merret</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore named, one likely to give a true account of their medicine making: you will find there a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue</hi> of great abuses, and counterfeiting of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines: and such safe medicines, the sick are plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully plyed with.</p>
            <p>To this we may add the thoughts and averment <note place="margin">The Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complisht Physician, &amp;c. pag. 8.</note> of an <hi>Anonymus Author</hi> of a late Tract, wherein touching this point in hand, he saith; <hi>At the Drug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gists there being two sorts of all Drugs, the one good sound and dear; the other, though of the same kind, course, almost rotten, and very cheap; we may be jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, that those who aim at an Aldermanship by a quick step, do for the most part make use of the latter sort of Drugs in all their Compositions, and in the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:42923:31"/> Preparations of the Prescripts of Physicians; whose bills its most certain are by some Apothecaries unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully dispensed, by adding a less quantity of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients, or such as will prove ineffectual, on design either to protract the course of Physick, or to defame the Physician.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to this purpose the forementioned <hi>Doctor</hi>
               <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Jonath. Goddards <hi>discourse,</hi> &amp;c. pag. 37.</note>
               <hi> Goddard</hi> saith, <hi>Let a Physician write the same Bill to several Shops, the Medicine shall be very different in the sensible qualities, scent, taste, colour, strength, pleasantness, &amp;c. according to the goodness of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients, or the cleanly and accurate making.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot let pass another testimony, which strikes home, and deeply wounds the repute of <hi>Shop Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines;</hi> and it is from an intelligent person of this Faculty; who in the current of his discourse, saith, <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Dan Cox <hi>his discourse of the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, &amp;c. pag. 246.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>This will be of high advantage to Physicians, and those Patients of theirs that live in the Country, where multitudes miscarry (and many even among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try) either under bad or for want of good Physick: For the Country Apothecaries not having certain vent for their Medicines, and few among them being well skilled in their Composition, to avoid charge and trouble, buy such things as they most frequently have occasion for, of</hi> London Apothecaries, <hi>who sell me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines cheaper than the others can make them; and well they may; they being either the refuse of their Shops, or fraudulently compounded; I mean, made either with old or perished Drugs, or else they leave out the most costly, which are often the most effectual and active ingredients. Now Physicians in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try comporting with the common way of sending Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scripts to the Apothecary, especially those that concern
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:42923:31"/> persons of quality; which Physick what effects it is like to have, I leave to others to conjecture; for my own part I will not affirm, that any are dispatched by it (though we have little reason to believe bad Physick can have good effects) but of this I am most certain, that it lets many dye (which is little better) whom pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balby it would have restored, had it been such as the Physician presumes the Apothecary is furnished with. And but that it is contrary to my nature, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign of this Discourse, to divulge any thing that might be a reproach to particular persons; I could name se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral gallant Gentlemen, exceedingly beloved in their Countrys, wherein they were very useful; who mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried, as is verily thought (by those that are compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent judges) between the neglect and baseness of the Country and City Apothecaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What do you think now of the <hi>Medicine Trade?</hi> and where is your reason for that confidence you have had in the supposed safety between a <hi>Doctor</hi> and an <hi>Apothecary:</hi> do you think you are not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter secured from common hazards, from the <hi>frauds, casualties,</hi> and <hi>abuses</hi> attending Medicines, under the charge of a <hi>Physician</hi> acting alone, than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two persons acting distinctly, whose diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent interests sway them two several ways? the <hi>Apothecary</hi> is no gainer by short and speedy Cures, wonder-working Medicines are nothing to him; that's the <hi>Doctors</hi> same and profit: but the <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries</hi> advantage lies in variety of <hi>sluggish dull</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, a <hi>tedious Cure,</hi> and a <hi>long Bill</hi> at the end of it: what is the <hi>Apothecary</hi> concerned for effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, brisk, generous medicines? they do him no good: fair and softly from <hi>spring</hi> to <hi>fall,</hi> and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:42923:32"/> from <hi>fall</hi> to <hi>spring</hi> again, that's best for him; a <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial</hi> is a <hi>Cordial,</hi> and a <hi>Bolus</hi> is a <hi>Bolus,</hi> good or bad, you must pay a good price: then what is the <hi>Apothecary</hi> concerned for <hi>Cures?</hi> Oh, let the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> look to that, that's his business; and if the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> were not a little infatuated, they would take a better course to effect their business. But in the mean time perhaps the <hi>Doctor</hi> goes under an ill name, and there is <hi>melancholly</hi> looks and <hi>grumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings</hi> for these <hi>slow</hi> doings: but the <hi>Apothecary</hi> comes <hi>innocently</hi> and briskly in, chears up the drooping <hi>Patient,</hi> tells him all will be well, but he must have patience; the <hi>Doctor</hi> takes a great deal of pains, comes often, and prescribes often; and for the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines they are, I marry are they: and now the Patient is cheered up, and pretty well satisfied; he is resolved to go on again, and try farther what can be done: so they jog on, and let them go.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Patients</hi> rightly and fully understood their own interest; they would force all <hi>Physicians</hi> to this duty of <hi>preparing</hi> their own medicines; from whom they might (for the reasons before mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) rest assured that their medicines were the <hi>best</hi> and most <hi>efficacious</hi> that <hi>Art, Care,</hi> and <hi>Money</hi> could procure and provide for them.</p>
            <p>But in the close of this <hi>Argument,</hi> I must clear off an objection that I have met with, framed by one of our own <hi>Faculty,</hi> and laid hold of by the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> in their <hi>Plea;</hi> urging it as a good <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument</hi> for their <hi>continuation;</hi> which is this: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians are mortal men and may (and ost have) in a debauched humour prescribe improper medicines, and most improportionate Doses, which an Apothecary by
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:42923:32"/> the experience of his Trade may discover, and repair for a rectification to the Physician next morning, when the Cloud is over with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answer </seg>
               </label> In former days there were two <hi>Collegiate Censors</hi> to overlook the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> and view their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines; yet all <hi>that</hi> could not prevent abuses: but <hi>aliares est,</hi> now the scene is changed and <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries</hi> will have it necessary, that they supervise the <hi>Doctors medicines,</hi> pass their judgment, and be <hi>monitors</hi> over them and their <hi>prescripts.</hi> Where are you now <hi>Doctor?</hi> have you not brought your Hogs to a fair Market? by this pretension no Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians <hi>Bill</hi> will be <hi>authentick,</hi> and of credit with the <hi>Patient,</hi> until it hath passed the <hi>Apothecaries ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation:</hi> and indeed the reliance on <hi>Apothecaries</hi> is arrived thus far already, that the <hi>Patient</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly asks the <hi>Apothecary's</hi> opinion concerning the <hi>Doctors</hi> abilities; whether he prescribes <hi>well</hi> or not: if he says <hi>well,</hi> 'tis <hi>well:</hi> if otherwise, turn out. The <hi>objection</hi> seems fair at first sight, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miseth weight; but being put into the ballance with the <hi>casualties, sophistications,</hi> and daily <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards</hi> that attend the dispensing and distributing <hi>Shop Medicines,</hi> will be found much too light, and these to <hi>preponderate,</hi> as being of greater mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and more frequently occurring. To come close to the point then, I grant you the <hi>objection</hi> thus far, that it is possible a Physician may be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seen in drink, and commit such an error as is alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: but what then? this is not enough to <hi>cashiere</hi> all Physicians from the <hi>management</hi> and <hi>charge</hi> of medicines: you must prove also, that the <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries</hi> and their Servants are never <hi>debauched,</hi> never
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:42923:33"/>
               <hi>overseen,</hi> nor <hi>mistaken,</hi> never <hi>abuse</hi> a Physicians <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>script;</hi> but are always <hi>exact, sober, careful,</hi> and <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest;</hi> when you have proved this, your <hi>objection</hi> is good, and carries force with it. But look back upon what is already said and proved, and you find little of this: and farther to <hi>counterpoise</hi> this objection, turn to the same <hi>Author</hi> that was pleased to dally with you, and see what he says in another place: (but take notice, it was this <hi>Gentleman</hi> that whipt some of your <hi>Apothecaries</hi> (the <hi>Authors</hi> of <note place="margin">A Lash for Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Talia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</note> that scurrilons Libel, <hi>Lex Talionis</hi>) for their sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciness towards <hi>Physicians,</hi> their <hi>quondam</hi> Masters; and admonished the rest pretty smartly) his words are these: <hi>The humour of a Tradesman to play the</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complisht Physician, &amp;c. p. 82.</note>
               <hi>Gentleman is too visible in many Apothecaries, who pass their time either Physician like in visiting Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, or rendring themselves to the recreations of the times, wherein they are plentifully supported by the revenue of their Shop, which their men manage, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the idleness and negligence Servants are all addicted to in the absence of their Masters: whence supposing a prescription to be erroneously or dangerously prepared, and the Patient upon the taking of it sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised with urgent symptoms, or yield to his last fate; it shall not be divulged to you, the man that made up the medicine was a raw apprentice, or had been drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drunk, whilst the Master was breathing his Nag in</hi> Hide Park; <hi>in all which transaction, its the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sician that must father the ill success.</hi> Now the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection is <hi>enervated</hi> and made <hi>invalid</hi> by him that offered it: and since there are such <hi>Apothecaries</hi> and such <hi>Servants;</hi> may not a sober Physician be affraid of trusting his <hi>prescripts</hi> in such hands, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:42923:33"/> venture the life of his Patient at these hazards? and may not the Patient be afraid, although he have an <hi>able</hi> and <hi>careful</hi> Physician, that the <hi>Apothecary</hi> may be negligent? and if he be a careful man when he is in his <hi>Shop;</hi> yet his <hi>Servants</hi> may be <hi>negligent, heedless,</hi> and <hi>mistake</hi> when he is abroad. How then must the <hi>Patient</hi> be secured, from the <hi>dangers</hi> and <hi>hazards</hi> that commonly attend medicines? I know no better, nor other way, but by making choice of such a <hi>Physician</hi> that is not addicted to <hi>intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> and <hi>debauchery,</hi> that is not a <hi>Tipler</hi> and <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial</hi> Companion, one that diligently follows his business, that <hi>seriously</hi> and <hi>soberly</hi> performs the whole duty of his employment, that trusts <hi>none</hi> in the choice of his ingredients, in <hi>dispensing, weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, preparing,</hi> and <hi>compounding,</hi> but all done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his <hi>eye,</hi> and in some nice things by his own <hi>hand:</hi> and then I think in all reason he is as likely to avoid all miscarriages and mistakes in medicines, as it is possible for man to do; and much more like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than <hi>Tradesmen</hi> and their <hi>Servants,</hi> in a perfun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory way of managing a Shop Trade; that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive how business may <hi>soonest</hi> and <hi>easiest</hi> be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spatcht, and turn to the best account for present gain. And so I dismiss the Patients interest in point of <hi>safety,</hi> and come to his other concern and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage in the matter of <hi>profit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This thing called <hi>profit</hi> is the general concern of the world, that all people hearken after, and design for; and some to save their <hi>purse</hi> will ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture their <hi>life:</hi> this <hi>profit</hi> perhaps may prove the <hi>strongest argument</hi> in the Book to perswade. <hi>Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> is not comparable to <hi>profit</hi> with a great many;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:42923:34"/> they had rather hazard their lives with a <hi>Chymical Empirick,</hi> a <hi>quacking Apothecary,</hi> or any <hi>illiterate</hi> fellow that pretends to Physick; hoping thereby to save <hi>charges,</hi> and cozen the <hi>Doctor</hi> of his <hi>Fees:</hi> and thus they cheat themselves, and are cheated by others. But to prevent such imprudent hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous courses, and to lessen the charge of Physick; the following discourse will inform you.</p>
            <p>That a <hi>course</hi> of Physick or <hi>fit</hi> of sickness will be less chargeable to the Patient, when both ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Physick depend upon the Physician; than when divided, and the charge distinct between two persons, appears plainly, if we consider,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>1</label>
               <hi>First,</hi> That the lessening of <hi>charge</hi> in all affairs <note place="margin">1. Argument.</note> is, by <hi>substracting</hi> and <hi>abating</hi> the number of <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> that are to be employed and maintained in that business: If <hi>one</hi> can manage it well and sufficiently, in vain is the expence to keep <hi>two</hi> upon such an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy; especially if <hi>two Families</hi> must be maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of it, and depend thereon; the <hi>charge</hi> then must needs be <hi>doubled</hi> and advanced high. For, admit both be <hi>honest,</hi> yet both must <hi>live</hi> upon it, gain sufficiently, and raise an <hi>estate</hi> for their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: if they be not honest, but <hi>covetously griping,</hi> and plotting how to gain most; such that make a <hi>prey</hi> of <hi>Patients,</hi> and are <hi>Purse-suckers:</hi> you may easily imagine then, that it is <hi>cheaper</hi> to be defraud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>one</hi> than by <hi>two;</hi> and it is better to satisfie the thirst of lucre in <hi>one,</hi> than in <hi>two</hi> persons: hence we may affirm as an undoubted truth, that it is much cheaper, and more saving for the Purse, to retain a Physician <hi>alone;</hi> than a Physician and an Apothecary <hi>together,</hi> whether <hi>honest,</hi> or <hi>dishonest.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:42923:34"/>
            <p>That this is a more chargeable and costly way, of taking Physick from <hi>two persons;</hi> appears in that Patients fall often into such a <hi>Physician</hi> and <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries</hi> hands, as <hi>combine</hi> together to promote each others interest. The Apothecary then makes it his business to commend and procure Patients to this able Doctor: This excellent Doctor to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taliate, makes him amends, by plying the Patient with good store, or rather much store of Physick: <hi>Who if he come three or four times a day, writes new</hi>
               <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> C. T. <hi>in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to a Letter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the practice of Physick in England.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Bills for the Apothecary; compound Glisters, rich cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial Juleps, Bolus's, Pearl, Bezoar, and Gold; words that signifie very much in augmenting the sum, at the foot of the account in an Apothecaries Bill, &amp;c.</hi> And Physicians that thus incline to gratifie and please Apothecaries, are called by them <hi>good Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Physicians;</hi> and if they be not so, then they shall not be <hi>good Doctors</hi> in their mouths; but the Apothecary will give him a lift if he can; at least, he will never cause him to be sent for again to this, nor any other Patient he can perswade; but some <hi>good Apothecaries Physician,</hi> or his own <hi>Covenant Physician</hi> must be the man. <hi>Now this good Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries Physician, they describe by his frequent though</hi>
               <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Merrets <hi>View of the frauds and abuses com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, &amp;c. pag. 15.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>needless visits; but especially the multitude of his Bills; by his visiting twice a day or oftner (a very careful and painful Doctor) and by still writing new medicines, when half the former or perhaps none of them have been taken; making an Apothecaries Shop in the Patients house, planting the Cupboard and Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow with Glasses and Gally-pots, and not a quarter of the whole made use of; he prescribes a medicine for every slight complaint, and never goes away from
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:42923:35"/> the Patient, or the Patient from him without a Bill, for fear of the Apothecaries grumbling.</hi> If it be so (as these Authors affirm) may we not justly suspect, when Physicians have a great <hi>voice</hi> and <hi>commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> amongst <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> that they are <hi>Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> good <hi>Physicians,</hi> not <hi>Patients</hi> good <hi>Physicians;</hi> and may we not well suspect that the great estates, and great names gotten by some Physicians did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise from <hi>hence,</hi> such <hi>artifices</hi> and <hi>combinations:</hi> and to confirm this rational belief, turn over their <hi>file</hi> of <hi>Bills,</hi> you will find there nothing <hi>great,</hi> but here and there <hi>great ignorance;</hi> you will there see such <hi>pitiful Recipe's</hi> and <hi>repetitions</hi> of them; that he which hath waded out of the mire of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon delusion, may bless himself; stand and admire that a learned profound <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>honourable Professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> should so strangely be abused; and the people doat so much to their great disadvantage and loss, and flock after (like silly Sheep) such <hi>grand Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postors:</hi> but the people have been, and are deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after this manner: What <hi>Doctor</hi> shall I have? says the <hi>sick man;</hi> ask the <hi>Apothecary,</hi> says another, he is most likely to tell you, who is an <hi>able Physician,</hi> and who you had best to send for: then comes the <hi>Apothecary</hi> and adviseth to his <hi>Covenant Physician,</hi> or if he be not approved of; then some one else, as good as he, that knows how the <hi>game</hi> must be <hi>plaid,</hi> to get the Apothecaries <hi>good word</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plause, and that will be gainful to him both now and hereafter; and by this <hi>Compass</hi> the Physician steers his course. Hence it is, that the most <hi>indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious</hi> and <hi>expert Physician</hi> practising with most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Medicines prepared by <hi>himself,</hi> is cryed
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:42923:35"/> down by all <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> and shall never be call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a <hi>Patient</hi> if they can keep him out; sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesting (very basely) that he is <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that;</hi> though he be a man of far greater merit and worth, in this Profession; able to out <hi>reason</hi> and out <hi>do</hi> a score of such <hi>Apothecary Doctors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This frequent jugling between <hi>Physicians</hi> and <hi>Apothecaries</hi> to promote the <hi>craft</hi> of Physick, I find confirmed by a late Writer before mentioned. <hi>Physicians all, or most, being tyed to particular Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complisht Physician, &amp;c. p. 74</note>
               <hi>prescribe their Bills in terms so obscure, that they force all chance Patients to repair to their own Apothecaries, pretending a particular secret, which only they have the Key to unlock; whereas in effect its no other than the commonest of Medicines, disguised under an unusual name, on design to direct you to an Apothecary, between whom and the Physician there is a private compact of going snips, out of the most unreasonable rates of the said Medicines, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in if you seek a redress by shewing the Bill to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, he shall most religiously aver, its the cheapest he ever read.</hi> You see here what great regard is had to the <hi>Patient</hi> all this while; what inventions found out and care taken to <hi>milk</hi> his <hi>Purse:</hi> O these are <hi>industrious</hi> men in <hi>Physick!</hi> such as the people put <hi>great confidence</hi> in! and to leave <hi>these men</hi> is as much as their <hi>lives</hi> are worth: A <hi>Doctor</hi> and <hi>Apothecary!</hi> can Physick be put into an <hi>honester</hi> and <hi>cheaper</hi> way? well go on then, <hi>per me licet;</hi> why should not every one have their <hi>Phansie,</hi> if they <hi>pay</hi> for it. What I have here written is not the design of my brain to asperse, but I give you the <hi>testimony</hi> (besides my <hi>sentiment</hi>) of <hi>learned
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:42923:36"/> Doctors,</hi> well reputed in this <hi>Faculty,</hi> now alive and practising in this <hi>City,</hi> that have been conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant with <hi>Apothecaries</hi> much <hi>longer</hi> than my self, and know very well the <hi>intrigues</hi> of this Practice. For my own part I was a <hi>Prescriber</hi> of Medicines to the <hi>Shops,</hi> for the first 8 or 9 years of my <hi>Practice,</hi> and did understand something in that time which made me desert them: but for this <hi>ten years</hi> or upwards I have used the Medicines of my own <hi>Preparation;</hi> so that having tryed both ways of Practice, I may give in my <hi>verdict</hi> too, what I know of them both, and let every one make choice of which they please.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, if you come to an Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Shop, for an ounce of <hi>Mithridate, Diascordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> or <hi>London Treacle,</hi> you may have it perhaps too <hi>cheap,</hi> but not too <hi>good;</hi> for the former old price is beaten down by underselling one another, to gain <hi>custom</hi> to the Shop: but you must know the <hi>medicine</hi> is according to the <hi>price;</hi> so that nothing is got by your cheap penny-worth. (<hi>Diascordium was found by the Censors in their search, made only of</hi>
               <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Merrets <hi>View of the frauds and abuses com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, &amp;c. pag. 9.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Honey and Bolearmeniac.</hi>) Yet this <hi>cheap sophisti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> Medicine, when you come to pay for it in a Physicians <hi>Prescript,</hi> it will then cost you six times so much, perhaps ten times so much, mixt in <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus's</hi> and <hi>Potions:</hi> O the <hi>Recipe's</hi> are very gainful, and when the <hi>Apothecary</hi> parts with these, the best stake in the hedge is gone: no body can tell the <hi>price</hi> of a <hi>Recipe;</hi> the quintessence of the Doctors learning is there, and the Apothecary will scorn to undervalue it now, when it is <hi>epitomized</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into a <hi>Recipe</hi> (though at another time
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:42923:36"/> Mr. <hi>Doctor</hi> is but <hi>so</hi> and <hi>so</hi> with him) I but <hi>Dias<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordium</hi> now is <hi>Diascordium</hi> indeed; you shall not buy it now for <hi>three pence</hi> an ounce, as you fetcht it the other day at the Shop: when a <hi>Dram</hi> or two is mixt with as much Conserve of Roses or White Lillies <hi>secundum Artem,</hi> it is a <hi>dormitive Bolus</hi> then; a thing which you do not understand; 'tis above the sphere of vulgar capacities: Here is <hi>Art,</hi> and here is the <hi>mystery</hi> of the Trade; this is our gain, and we are necessary <hi>Appendants</hi> to Physick; <hi>opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serque per orbem dicor,</hi> says Mr. Apothecary; <hi>idest,</hi> the Doctor can do nothing without us. Now sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose (excepting the Doctors Fee) the price of this <hi>Bolus</hi> be but half a Crown: you'l say that is not much for a good Medicine by advice: I'le reckon it to you, then judge if you be not used kindly: two pence for the <hi>Diascordium</hi> and <hi>Conserve,</hi> and <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven groats</hi> for mixing <hi>secundum Artem,</hi> that's just half a Crown; cheap enough! but I find a <hi>Colledge Doctor</hi> complaining of the chargeableness of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick, in this <hi>Apothecary</hi> way of Practice, and says; <hi>The charge of it is often insupportable, as well as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conscionable</hi>
               <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> C. T. <hi>his Answer to a Letter &amp;c. p. 18.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>and uncharitable; we many times pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe a dram of Treacle worth two pence to a poor neighbour out of charity; the Apothecary makes him pay half a Crown for a Cordial Bolus. There are of us, have retrieved some of our Prescriptions, and the Apothecaries Bills upon them, you will perhaps be amazed when I tell you; that where a Physician hath without a Fee prescribed something worth six pence; because it was made into twenty four Pills, there was so many shillings paid to the Apothecary upon his Bill for it; but I will give you no more accounts of this
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:42923:37"/> kind now, you may in good time see store of them, upon proofs beyond denial.</hi> I perceive now by these ugly hints, there is Rods in piss; and 'tis like there may come a day of reckoning for such <hi>faults.</hi> However in the mean time, we <hi>vulgar</hi> will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, but this <hi>Apothecary</hi> way is the <hi>cheapest</hi> and <hi>best</hi> way of Physicking.</p>
            <p>Another Doctor of the Colledge, a Practiser for 30 years with Apothecaries, complains after the same rate: <hi>Suppose a Physician hath prescribed a</hi>
               <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Merret <hi>in his view &amp;c p. 16.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>pint of Julep, &amp;c. to be taken at four several times; some Apothecaries carry not the whole pint at once; but divide it into four parts, and carry but one at a time, and so of other Medicines; and then will charge his Bill for every single potion or draught, as he ought the whole pint; so that by this art he gains four times as much for the whole medicine, as in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science he ought; and a Julep which cost him six pence, will be rated at ten, twelve or more shillings, &amp;c,</hi> so he goes on setting forth their unreasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prices and profit by Physicians Prescripts. I find now that this <hi>Apothecary</hi> Trade is a very <hi>thriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> gainful Trade; and the <hi>Patients</hi> Trade is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>doleful</hi> losing Trade, and very liable to <hi>Cheats.</hi> It is much better to be an <hi>Apothecary</hi> than a <hi>Patient;</hi> and it is much <hi>cheaper</hi> to take Physick from a <hi>Doctors hand,</hi> than from his <hi>hand-writing.</hi> These <hi>Recipe's</hi> I see are costly things: sure they were intended only for <hi>Ladies</hi> and <hi>great persons;</hi> that must be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with Physicians and Apothecaries both; that must dye in state. I cannot see how other people can well bear this charge: but we are all grown so proud now, that if it be the fashion for
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:42923:37"/> the <hi>great</hi> ones to have a <hi>Recipe Doctor,</hi> we vulgar will have a <hi>Recipe Doctor</hi> too, what ever it cost us. We will have all the <hi>Formalities</hi> of Physick though we dye for it (and like enough, all <hi>casualties</hi> and <hi>deceits</hi> considered which attend that Practice.) But let us examine these high priced <hi>Recipe's</hi> a little, and see the great <hi>worth</hi> of them; because there is great <hi>talk,</hi> and a great <hi>bustle</hi> about them: but now you talk of <hi>worth,</hi> they must be valued by what they <hi>cost,</hi> as for <hi>intrinsic</hi> worth let that pass, meddle not there: Now imagine we were at a file of Bills.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Recipe</hi> cost the Patient <hi>ten shillings</hi> Fee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he was but a Doctor of <hi>little</hi> practice, not <hi>cryed</hi> up, and that was fair for him. As for the <hi>Apothecary</hi> you may imagine (by what goes before) that he will be no loser by it; though he gets (if you will believe it) but a small inconsiderable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. Here's another cost a <hi>Guiny</hi> (besides the mans <hi>life</hi>) this was a <hi>great Doctor's,</hi> one of the eminentest in the Town, a man of very <hi>great Practice,</hi> that you must wait two hours before you can speak with him, except you give his man a couple of shillings; this must needs be an able man, that the people croud after, much spoken of, and much approved by his <hi>Apothecary,</hi> who gets four or five hundred pounds <hi>per annum</hi> by this <hi>Doctor's</hi> Practice: an excellent <hi>Apothecary Doctor!</hi> he deserved a piece very gallantly. But here is a <hi>Recipe</hi> cost 3 <hi>Guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies;</hi> this was the result of a <hi>consultation,</hi> for a person of quality, a beloved Child, Wife, or Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, or some rich fellow that would <hi>dye</hi> more <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onourably</hi> than ever he had lived: Here's another
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:42923:38"/>
               <hi>golden Recipe</hi> of the same price, for the same Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that evening, a <hi>Cordial dormitive Bolus:</hi> Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this was very <hi>cordial</hi> Physick (to the <hi>Physicians</hi>) there was so much Gold about it: Here is three or four more <hi>Recipe's</hi> for the same Patient, that smells of extracted <hi>Gold</hi> very precious: but the last of them was the highest <hi>Shop Cordial</hi> that could be made: So that you may imagine what condition the <hi>Patient</hi> was in when the <hi>Physicians</hi> took their leave: Surely, these <hi>Recipe's</hi> are very fine things, they are so costly: but who pays the <hi>Apothecary</hi> all this while? O! the <hi>Executor</hi> pays him, that is to be done after the <hi>Funeral conclusion:</hi> there's a lump of money indeed to be received! perhaps this man gets more after the Patients <hi>death,</hi> than three Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors in his <hi>life</hi> time; it often falls out so (without jesting.) Give me leave to quote an <hi>Author</hi> now, something pertinent to our purpose (without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon the persons named) not as a parallel example to our Discourse in the particulars; but only to let you know upon <hi>proof,</hi> that the <hi>medicine trade</hi> goes beyond the <hi>medical Art,</hi> in extracting Gold and Silver very wonderfully.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> C. T. <hi>in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to a Letter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the practice of Physick in England. pag 46.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>It is some years since, when Doctor</hi> Pursean, <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> Bates, <hi>and my self, for three or four weeks at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance on a person of quality, received in Fees three or four and thirty pounds; they being consulters some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times only; and I ordinary Physician had more than half of that sum: I believe my self, the person was well, and well satisfied, until the Apothecaries Bill was brought in; but then I was called to the ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful work of judging upon the prices of it; I was a little started to find the sum total five and fifty pounds;
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:42923:38"/> and I do assure you I speak moderately, when I say, if he were paid it, his gain was as much as the three Physicians received; but it was an Apothecary of the Patients own choice, and I had nothing to answer for it.</hi> This is not fair play, Mr. <hi>Apothecary,</hi> that you should get more than three <hi>Doctors:</hi> yours is a cunning Trade indeed; and I do not so much wonder now, that so many <hi>Apothecaries</hi> set up, since it is such a gainful Trade and honest income, of eighty and ninety <hi>per Cent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You see how cheap the taking of Physick is with a <hi>Physician</hi> and <hi>Apothecary</hi> together: let us now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire farther, if any money can be saved by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying to a <hi>Practising Apothecary,</hi> one that will Physick you by his own advice, and save you the charge of <hi>Fees</hi> (if you think good to believe it.) To wave their <hi>inability</hi> to practice, and the <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous consequences</hi> that attend their bold quack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (<note n="*" place="margin">Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plisht Phys. pag. 45, 46 47, 48.</note>
               <hi>as many fatal actions do testifie, and some mentioned by a late Writer</hi>) I shall speak only as to the <hi>Patients profit,</hi> chiefly aimed at by them that apply to these <hi>Tradesmen</hi> in Physick for their assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance. Some think it a notable convenience to have recourse to an <hi>Apothecaries Shop,</hi> upon small occasions for medicines, without the charge of a Physicians <hi>advice</hi> and <hi>Prescript.</hi> To this I say, the convenience is not what people imagine, and no charge saved thereby; if we suppose instead there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, Physicians to be furnished with <hi>necessary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Medicines</hi> for all occasions, as I have urged that duty upon them: is it not then as <hi>convenient?</hi> will it not then be as <hi>cheap?</hi> will not your medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines be far <hi>better?</hi> will it not be more <hi>safe</hi> and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:42923:39"/>
               <hi>expeditious</hi> for your <hi>help</hi> and <hi>relief,</hi> to come or send to the Physician for <hi>his Medicines,</hi> who for his own reputation and special interest (as is fully proved <hi>pag.</hi> 53.) will give you the best medicine or medicines faithfully and effectually prepared for your purpose, and also advise you how to use them for the best advantage, at as <hi>cheap</hi> a rate, as at the <hi>Apothecaries;</hi> yes much <hi>cheaper</hi> and more <hi>advantagious,</hi> if you consider the <hi>ability</hi> of the <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sician</hi> above the <hi>Apothecary;</hi> and the rational pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of his medicines, to be much <hi>better</hi> and more <hi>efficacious;</hi> both which, facilitate and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite a <hi>cure,</hi> or check an <hi>emergent grievance,</hi> which are to be reckoned in the account of <hi>Costs,</hi> as a great advantage above the <hi>Shop</hi> Medicines and <hi>Shop</hi> Master: So that the Physicians <hi>Repository,</hi> or Closet accommodation, is as ready, as <hi>cheap</hi> or <hi>cheaper,</hi> and as <hi>commodious</hi> to repair to, as the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries</hi> Shop, only the one stands in view, the other private, yet easie enough to be known, when the custom shall be made general: and it is as <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> a way, and <hi>easie</hi> for the Physician, to bid his <hi>man</hi> give the Patient such a <hi>Medicine,</hi> as to write a <hi>Recipe</hi> to the Apothecary. That people are much deluded, in thinking they save charges, by applying to a <hi>practising Apothecary,</hi> is set forth by the foregoing Author from <hi>pag.</hi> 65. to 73. and it <note place="margin">Accomp. Physician.</note> is but reason they should pay notably for their folly. Dr. <hi>Merret</hi> does caution the same: but <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus vult decipi:</hi> and if people will not be admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, let them fall into the <hi>cheat</hi> without pity. <hi>And at how easie rates they practise, many of their</hi>
               <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Merrets <hi>view, &amp;c. pag. 49.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Bills brought and complained of to our Colledge witness,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:42923:39"/> wherein upon a slight disease five pounds have been demanded for four days Practice. And I have heard one of them brag, that he commonly had from 20 to an hundred pounds, besides presents, for cure of a Clap (as they call it) which might have been more speedily and securely performed for a manifold lesser sum.</hi> If you come as a <hi>Customer</hi> to the Shop, and ask for an ordinary known <hi>Shop Medicine;</hi> you shall have it for an <hi>ordinary price:</hi> but when you come as a Patient, take his advice, and such me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines from him that you know not; then you shall pay <hi>roundly</hi> for <hi>both; Counsel</hi> as well as <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might inlarge here upon this point, but I will pass over much, to finish this <hi>Paragraph</hi> briefly. I appeal now to all that are <hi>unbiassed</hi> and <hi>impartial;</hi> and let every one of common reason judge, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not a much <hi>cheaper</hi> and a more <hi>frugal</hi> way, to apply to a Physician <hi>alone,</hi> furnished with honest good medicines (as it is his interest) than to a <hi>Physician</hi> and <hi>Apothecary,</hi> or to an Apothecary <hi>alone:</hi> if you say we cannot be assured that a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sician acting <hi>alone,</hi> deals honestly and consciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with us: then I reply to you again; nor can you be assured that a <hi>Physician</hi> and his <hi>Apothecary</hi> deals honestly with you: 'tis the same uncertainty here as there, and rather the <hi>more hazardous</hi> for the reasons aforesaid. And since <hi>honesty</hi> is so hard to find, and <hi>dishonesty</hi> so difficult to discover, (but you must <hi>venture:</hi>) then I think it is more <hi>prudent,</hi> and <hi>cheaper</hi> to venture upon one <hi>Knave,</hi> (supposing so) than two: since <hi>both</hi> must be gainers; <hi>one</hi> at a time is enough to cozen you. And if you
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:42923:40"/> compare a practising Apothecary <hi>alone,</hi> with a Physician <hi>alone:</hi> have you not more reason to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side in and believe the <hi>latter</hi> (legally called there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and well qualified) that he will be honester and more reasonable in his dealing than the <hi>former,</hi> whose very undertaking is a <hi>dishonest</hi> and an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just</hi> way of living: his presumptuous usurped <hi>Practice</hi> is a constant <hi>cheating</hi> of Physicians, who gave him his Trade: then in all reasonable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability he will not stick to <hi>cheat Patients,</hi> from whom there is no such obligation. He that will be so <hi>perfidious</hi> and <hi>ungrateful</hi> (manifestly in the sight of the world) to <hi>him</hi> that set him up; will not boggle to <hi>cheat</hi> a silly <hi>Patient,</hi> that cannot detect him: and therefore let none be so vain and foolish to say of a <hi>practising Apothecary</hi> that he is an <hi>honest man;</hi> for, to be <hi>honest</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> are incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible and a contradiction. If you would know more of this <hi>Practising Apothecary,</hi> you will find him described in a Tract of mine (amongst the number of other <hi>Practisers</hi>) put forth about three <note place="margin">Medicus Absolutus.</note> years since; where he stands in his colours, from <hi>pag.</hi> 50. to 64.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>2</label>
               <hi>Secondly, Charge</hi> and <hi>Cost</hi> is abated, by contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and lessening the <hi>number</hi> or <hi>quantity</hi> of <hi>mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials,</hi> to be employed and used in the performance of any work; and so <hi>è contra:</hi> and thus it is in the different Practices and Controversie in hand. The <hi>multiplying</hi> of medicines in the <hi>Prescribing</hi> Practice to Apothecaries, does much <hi>increase</hi> the <hi>charge</hi> of Physick, above <hi>that</hi> of the Physician <hi>alone</hi> with his Medicines: First, in regard the <hi>Prescriber</hi> is urged and tempted to this unnecessary accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:42923:40"/> by the <hi>Apothecary</hi> for his <hi>profit,</hi> and to <hi>please</hi> him (as appears plainly in pag. 63) Secondly, the <hi>Shop Medicines</hi> are <hi>slugglish, inefficacious,</hi> and <hi>unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully</hi> made (as appears <hi>p.</hi> 55, 56) therefore in reason, you must allow them <hi>more</hi> in number, and <hi>more often</hi> to be repeated (although the Physician be <hi>honest</hi> to his Patient) before they can effect any thing to the purpose aimed at.</p>
            <p>But the Physician that is <hi>Pharmacopoeian</hi> to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, that prepares Medicines faithfully and exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitely; does not use <hi>half</hi> that <hi>number</hi> of Medicines: he delights not in the superfluous <hi>variety</hi> and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>slight</hi> medicines; but he aims at a <hi>few choice</hi> and <hi>efficacious</hi> ones, to perform such operations that nature requires for her assistance; and those are not many: and knowing that nature must be relieved by such and such an <hi>operation;</hi> and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well <hi>tryed</hi> medicines to perform those intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he prosecutes them with his approved certain medicines; and is not <hi>varying</hi> at every turn, nor <hi>coyning</hi> new medicines every day, to <hi>cheat</hi> the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient into a belief, that here is <hi>not able</hi> contrivances, and <hi>extraordinary Art</hi> used; but sticks close to two <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Aph. 52. Sect. 2.</hi>
               </note> or three good medicines that the case requires; and plys his Patient with them in due <hi>order</hi> and rational <hi>method,</hi> until nature be <hi>relieved,</hi> or that he be well satisfied of the <hi>contumacy</hi> of the disease resisting and contemning those medicines, or a difficult <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teroclital</hi> propriety of body, <hi>enforcing</hi> him to <hi>change</hi> his medicines; which is not <hi>presently</hi> to be done, but after some considerable time of tryal; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring herein that <hi>Aphorism</hi> of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> where he cautions you not to be <hi>fickle</hi> and <hi>lightly</hi> to change
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:42923:41"/> medicines; if upon good grounds and a well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed judgment, you have instituted your course. So that a Physician by this fixt rational way of proceeding, with well <hi>experienced</hi> medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines of his own <hi>elaborate preparation,</hi> that he can confide in and rely on; he waits with patience, expecting the <hi>full tryal</hi> of their operations and suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess; having no <hi>sinister</hi> dishonest ends to tempt him aside (as appears <hi>pag.</hi> 52, 53) to make a <hi>bustle</hi> with <hi>variety</hi> of medicines, thereby to cause <hi>fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent</hi> visits, for multiplying his own <hi>Fees,</hi> and to <hi>advantage</hi> an Apothecary by <hi>accumulating</hi> medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines unnecessarily: but he labours to get <hi>same</hi> to his own medicines (wherein lies his profit and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light) and therefore puts them upon the <hi>full tryal</hi> and extent of their power; which cannot be, if he <hi>whiffle</hi> to and fro, <hi>chop</hi> and <hi>change;</hi> but keeps a <hi>steady</hi> course, if no <hi>accident</hi> fall out to disturb him; and it is his great concern, that no medicine be <hi>baffied</hi> or <hi>defamed,</hi> in the <hi>operation</hi> or intended <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect;</hi> but if that will perform the work, let it have the deserved credit; and then not to <hi>change</hi> or <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> will redound highly to the Physicians advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and praise of such medicines; <hi>frustra fit per plura, quod fieri potest per pauciora.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>3</label>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Much <hi>attendance</hi> in any affair, aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the <hi>charge:</hi> So is it in the <hi>Prescribing Practice;</hi> daily and often <hi>visits,</hi> requires frequent <hi>rewards:</hi> and lest the <hi>Patient</hi> should think the <hi>Doctor</hi> does not deserve his <hi>Fee,</hi> for only <hi>looking</hi> on him; he sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom takes his leave but he puts the <hi>Patient</hi> to the <hi>cost</hi> of another <hi>Recipe</hi> (though needless) in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change for his <hi>Accipe;</hi> and then the <hi>Apothecary</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:42923:41"/> is <hi>pleased</hi> too, into the bargain; and by this he shall merit the Title of a very <hi>careful Doctor,</hi> and have his good word to back him, and help him at a dead lift, if suddenly or unexpectedly the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent makes his <hi>exit</hi> into <hi>terra incognita.</hi> And truly it is something necessary that this <hi>Doctor</hi> who often deals with <hi>excogitated</hi> new <hi>minted</hi> medicines <hi>pro re nata;</hi> such as he never tryed, but are recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him by this or that <hi>Author,</hi> in parallel cases; or are the product of his own <hi>Pha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sie</hi> and <hi>proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility,</hi> adapted to the present <hi>syndrom</hi> of indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; all which is but a probable <hi>adventure, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> and no <hi>certainty</hi> or confidence, until tryal puts you out of fear. It is necessary then the <hi>Doctor</hi> should attend the <hi>event</hi> of these uncertain medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, which often proves <hi>unexpected;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he must be <hi>ready,</hi> he must be at hand, to <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect</hi> what happens amiss, and to cast about for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>invention,</hi> if this fails: but put the case this <hi>Doctor</hi> does use a certain medicine, that he hath often tryed; yet if he have not a <hi>certain, honest, skilful Apothecary,</hi> his medicine may fail him: and if he chance to have such a <hi>certain Apothecary;</hi> yet if he have not a <hi>certain, understanding, careful</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries <hi>Boy,</hi> his tryed good medicine, may very likely <hi>Deceive</hi> him: therefore he must always be at the <hi>heels</hi> of his medicine, to know what opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and what success; and therefore this <hi>Doctor</hi> knocks at the door, with <hi>doubtful</hi> and <hi>timorous</hi> thoughts (as there is reason for it) except he be as bold as blind <hi>Bayard:</hi> and for this his daily <hi>care,</hi> he must have daily <hi>Fees,</hi> which makes a course of Physick too <hi>chargeable</hi> for some Patients: and not
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:42923:42"/> only so; but the Apothecary must be paid for his kind <hi>visits</hi> too, but those are commonly crouded into the <hi>price</hi> of medicines; that although you take no notice of it, yet your <hi>Purse</hi> feels it; and now you may account your self as at the charge of <hi>two Doctors.</hi> But <hi>è contra,</hi> that <hi>Physician</hi> which practiseth with the medicines of his <hi>own prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> made choice of the <hi>ingredients,</hi> saw their due <hi>ordering</hi> and <hi>managing</hi> of them into medicine; that hath often <hi>proved, meliorated,</hi> &amp; knows well the <hi>certainty</hi> of their operation; dares trust his medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, and appoint them confidently with great <hi>safety</hi> (in <hi>chronick</hi> diseases) although he be an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred miles distant: and this I have done <hi>frequently</hi> with good <hi>success;</hi> and in such cases, when the <hi>Physicians</hi> of their <hi>Country,</hi> that have had the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of daily <hi>visiting</hi> and observing all <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances</hi> attending the Disease, and the <hi>operations</hi> of their medicines, could effect nothing: as <hi>letters</hi> of intercourse, that lye by me, can <hi>testifie.</hi> And I doubt not but other <hi>Physicians,</hi> who use their <hi>own medicines</hi> can say the like; that they can trust their medicines in their <hi>absence</hi> from the Patient; and practice with such a freedom and safety, without a <hi>constant attendance:</hi> and therefore I must affirm, it is much <hi>better</hi> and <hi>safer,</hi> that the Physician <hi>constant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>severely</hi> attend the <hi>medicine,</hi> rather than the <hi>Patient,</hi> if he cannot attend both.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>4</label>
               <hi>Fourthly, Expedition</hi> and a quick performance of <note place="margin">4. Argument.</note> any work, is reckoned and accounted in the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit;</hi> by how much <hi>sooner</hi> the business is effected, so much <hi>charge</hi> is <hi>abated.</hi> And thus it is in our case in hand: a <hi>Pharmacopoeian</hi> Physician acting
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:42923:42"/>
               <hi>alone,</hi> as he is more <hi>able</hi> and <hi>expert</hi> in curing above the <hi>Apothecary Doctor;</hi> so also his medicines are more efficacious and more certain in their opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, than the Shop Medicines (proved <hi>pag.</hi> 51, 52, 53.) from whence in all reason, cures will be effected more <hi>expeditiously</hi> and <hi>sooner.</hi> Besides his interest puts him on to a <hi>speedy</hi> relief of the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent: but the Apothecaries interest does not spur him on to such hasty and expeditious performances (proved <hi>pag.</hi> 57. 58.) therefore the business of curing in all probability and reason, moves much <hi>slower</hi> in the hands of <hi>two</hi> persons than in <hi>one;</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be against the Proverb; <hi>that many hands make light work;</hi> but in this case we may fear <hi>slight</hi> work, and <hi>slow</hi> work.</p>
            <p>Now by what hath been said, you may easily imagine how the <hi>great charge</hi> of Physick may be <hi>abated;</hi> and which is the <hi>cheapest</hi> course and most <hi>frugal</hi> way; and not inferior to any other; but <hi>excelling</hi> also any other in <hi>safety,</hi> and in what may be accounted <hi>excellent</hi> in Physick. And so I pass on to the next considerable <hi>inforcement</hi> of this duty of <hi>preparing Medicines</hi> by <hi>Physicians;</hi> and <note place="margin">3. Enforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> that ariseth from the <hi>benefits</hi> that accrue to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Advan∣tage. </seg>1</label> The <hi>advantages</hi> that redound to the <hi>Professors</hi> from their industry in the preparation of various medicines are: <hi>First,</hi> a familiar <hi>acquaintance</hi> with, and knowledge of the <hi>materia medica:</hi> that all the ingredients of Medicines, Drugs, or what else appertains to, or enters their composition, may not be <hi>strangers</hi> to them; but <hi>prima facie</hi> upon sight thereof, and with a discerning eye, they
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:42923:43"/> may distinguish rightly one <hi>kind</hi> from another; as also accurately the various <hi>differences</hi> of the same <hi>species</hi> in point of <hi>goodness:</hi> whereby they may be able to make a true <hi>election</hi> and choice, of the <hi>good</hi> and finest; from the <hi>degenerate</hi> mean sort, <hi>ungar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,</hi> decayed by long keeping or otherwise dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maged; which is a very considerable matter, and of great importance in order to curing: for, if the ingredients of a medicine be not thus <hi>judiciously</hi> and <hi>honestly</hi> chosen, there cannot reasonably be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected a good <hi>success</hi> from medicines otherwise made; since every thing operates <hi>quantum in se, &amp; pro viribus,</hi> according to the degree of its goodness or pravity. And father, it derogates much from the <hi>skill</hi> and <hi>compleatness</hi> of any Artist, not to know upon sight and appearance, all the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments</hi> and <hi>materials</hi> that belong to his Art: and therefore it must needs be a great <hi>deficiency</hi> in a Physician, and it is very absurd, that he should ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point such things for his <hi>Patient,</hi> to which he is a <hi>stranger,</hi> and knows them not when he sees them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Advan∣tage. </seg>2</label>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Hereby not only the <hi>face</hi> and external <note place="margin">Second ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</note>
               <hi>characters</hi> of the ingredients of medicines are known, but also by their several <hi>preparations</hi> and <hi>union</hi> this with that, diversiy varied; many <hi>secret properties</hi> are discovered, <hi>simply</hi> as in themselves and genuine nature; and <hi>relatively</hi> or respectively as they are yoked and compounded variously with one another: which most requisite and necessary knowledge is <hi>lost,</hi> if the Physician be not an <hi>opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> in Medicines. For all the <hi>Philosophical artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial</hi> knowledge we have of Medicines, comes in this way, (that which meerly results from proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:42923:43"/> in diseases, is empyrical) and this is the <hi>ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work</hi> and <hi>foundation</hi> upon which medicines are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed and neatly framed. And that <hi>Physician</hi> who spends some time in <hi>Pharmacy,</hi> shall find more sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in seeing a medicine duly prepared and <hi>compounded once,</hi> than in reading of it a <hi>twelve month:</hi> nor can the true proportion and quantity of each ingredient <hi>exactly</hi> be known, suting with the design and form of the medicine, by <hi>study</hi> and <hi>guessing,</hi> but by <hi>proofs</hi> and <hi>tryals</hi> in making. From hence the particular properties and differing qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of each ingredient will more plainly and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be discovered in their several <hi>preparations, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, defaecations, extractions, analytical resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp;c.</hi> here you may learn and know the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>results</hi> from different commixtures: the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fict</hi> and <hi>discrepancy</hi> of some, the <hi>amity</hi> and <hi>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces</hi> of others; the <hi>rejection</hi> and <hi>incoibility</hi> of some; but reducible into <hi>composition</hi> by fit <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums</hi> and artificial conjunction. And without this experimental knowledge, the <hi>forming</hi> and <hi>adapt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> medicines <hi>pro re nata</hi> for several cases, is so <hi>blind</hi> an <hi>adventure,</hi> that a Physician may well blush at his <hi>ignorance,</hi> and always fear his <hi>misfortunes,</hi> in running amongst dangers without a <hi>guide.</hi> For by the <hi>preparation</hi> of medicinal ingredients various ways, and by divers <hi>Commixtures</hi> of this with that, observing their several <hi>results</hi> and effects upon dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent <hi>associations</hi> and <hi>preparations;</hi> we then esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish a certain compleat knowledge upon such <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments;</hi> which surely guides us in the <hi>same</hi> for the future, as also directs us in <hi>collateral tryals,</hi> and <hi>processes</hi> of affinity. Then ought we not to trust
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:42923:44"/>
               <hi>fallacious tradition</hi> and the <hi>uncertain reports</hi> of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors (which deceives many and often) but by <hi>viewing, handling, tasting, smelling,</hi> and such like examinations throughout the process of the more exquisite and <hi>Chymical</hi> preparations; a sensible and full satisfaction in the different properties of the <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teria medica</hi> is gained: which great <hi>advantages</hi> and <hi>opportunities</hi> of knowledge, a <hi>traditional pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing</hi> Physician or <hi>Apothecary</hi> Doctor, gives away to his <hi>operator</hi> or <hi>Apothecary;</hi> who being not <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable,</hi> and to whom it does not <hi>belong</hi> as his busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to make such nice observations, but <hi>hoc agere,</hi> according to his prescript: much knowledge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>perisheth,</hi> and great opportunities of improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are <hi>lost;</hi> and such a Physician always sticks in the mire of <hi>doubts</hi> and <hi>uncertainties:</hi> and out of 40 or 50 years <hi>Practice</hi> he shall raise but a <hi>small stock</hi> of a compleat certain knowledge. If it be so, as true it is: then why Physicians should neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect these great <hi>offers</hi> of improvement, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of their knowledge in the most <hi>intricate</hi> and weightiest part of this <hi>Science;</hi> deserting the <hi>ancient</hi> constitution and <hi>true</hi> Practice of Physick, the most <hi>safe</hi> and <hi>rational,</hi> upon which this <hi>Art</hi> is founded and built, exchanging for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent fashion of <hi>prescribing</hi> and <hi>filing</hi> Bills with <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries;</hi> a late unhappy <hi>innovation,</hi> unwarily and unreasonably introduced, of <hi>pernicious</hi> conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents to this <hi>Science,</hi> the <hi>Professors,</hi> and the <hi>Sick;</hi> is to me, and may be to all others a wonder.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Advan∣tage. </seg>3</label>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that he may render a more <hi>rational</hi> and <note place="margin">3. Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</note> better account of <hi>diseases,</hi> and their true manner of curing; enabling him thereby to <hi>design</hi> and <hi>adapt</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:42923:44"/> medicines more <hi>knowingly</hi> and <hi>certainly</hi> to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of any Disease, than it is possible for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to do. A Physicians knowledge is not only improved in <hi>Pharmacy,</hi> by <hi>Pharmaceutick</hi> Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and this Art of medicinal preparations (<hi>Chymical</hi> chiefly) restrained only to the artificial making of medicines, and the advantages limited here; but is very <hi>extensive</hi> and <hi>assistant</hi> through the whole <hi>Science</hi> of Physick; becomes very use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and auxiliary to a Physician, in <hi>facilitating</hi> his disquisition, and <hi>improving</hi> his knowledge in the nature of diseases; discovering their several pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties and differences (as is set forth in pag. 9, 10, 11, 12.) and confirming his judgment in their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of curing. For example, if a man be griped in his <hi>stomack</hi> or <hi>belly,</hi> provoking a flux, and this is quieted and checkt by exhibiting of <hi>oculi can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crorum, corallium,</hi> or such like: it is concluded rationally, that a <hi>luxuriant acidity</hi> did cause those punctures and laxitive motions, because these <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes</hi> do satiate and drink up all <hi>acidities</hi> by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of their <hi>Alkaly:</hi> now here was a right adapta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of medicine to the morbific cause, proved by the <hi>genuine property</hi> of the remedy; and this <hi>alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisate</hi> property was first discovered by <hi>preparation</hi> and <hi>tryals;</hi> mixing <hi>alkalies</hi> with <hi>acids,</hi> the acidity is destroyed, that punging quality extinct, and the liquor becomes blunt and insipid as water; and as it is thus in this particular, so likewise in many other medicines; the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of their virtues and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations are not <hi>truly known</hi> and <hi>fathomed,</hi> but by <hi>tryals</hi> in the <hi>laboratory,</hi> which discovers many of their <hi>single</hi> properties, their <hi>result</hi> in mixture, and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:42923:45"/> their <hi>manner</hi> of opposing and allaying Diseases. It is not sufficient praise that a Physician does <hi>cure</hi> (one that is no Physician, does that by <hi>chance</hi> and sometimes) but that he be able to give a good ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional account <hi>how</hi> he <hi>cures;</hi> which he cannot do if he have not a <hi>perspective</hi> compleat knowledge of the <hi>medicine,</hi> collated with the <hi>nature</hi> of the Disease, (gained as aforesaid) else he is like an <hi>Empirick,</hi> and he derogates from his Title of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi> and the <hi>dignity</hi> of this Profession.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Advan∣tage. </seg>4</label>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That he may improve his knowledge by Practice, in making <hi>certain observations</hi> upon <hi>medicines</hi> after operation, whether <hi>successful, fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straneous,</hi> or of ill <hi>consequence:</hi> he may then upon good grounds <hi>commend, excuse,</hi> or <hi>condemn</hi> any medicines (which a <hi>Prescriber</hi> cannot) being <hi>privy</hi> to all things appertaining thereto, the <hi>making</hi> as well as the <hi>designment:</hi> so that all things being <hi>naked</hi> before him, nothing hinders or is doubtful, but he may give a true account of the <hi>failure</hi> or <hi>success,</hi> and where it ought to be imputed. But he that practiseth with <hi>unknown Shop Medicines,</hi> may be glad of his fortunate success, yet knows not what to <hi>praise,</hi> except <hi>God Almighty:</hi> and if the <hi>contrary</hi> happen he shall not be satisfied where the <hi>fault</hi> was; whether in the <hi>medicine</hi> that was ill made, or in <hi>himself</hi> that designed it; or <hi>idiosyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratical propriety</hi> of the Patient; <hi>contumacy</hi> of the disease, or <hi>intervening accidents;</hi> nor can he note that an <hi>observation</hi> for the future: So that he which practiseth thus at <hi>hap hazard,</hi> who cannot make a <hi>true observation</hi> to direct or warn him for the future; is always a <hi>young</hi> Practiser, and a <hi>new beginner</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:42923:45"/> 30 or 40 years <hi>blundering</hi> in Physick; nor can he be relyed on, or truly accounted as an <hi>able, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced, old</hi> Physician: but this character of an <hi>old</hi> Practiser goes far in the opinion of most people, as a safe man to trust their lives with; when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed most commonly he is but such a <hi>Tyro</hi> or <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi> as I have described; and an industrious <hi>Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macopoeian</hi> Physician rightly <hi>principled,</hi> of <hi>seven years</hi> practice, is well able to be his <hi>Master.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Advan∣tage. </seg>5</label>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That he may acquire and purchase to himself, <hi>far better</hi> and more <hi>excellent medicines</hi> than those of the <hi>Shops,</hi> or other common <hi>tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional</hi> medicines; which will most deservedly raise his <hi>fame</hi> and <hi>reputation,</hi> and render him more <hi>ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable</hi> and more <hi>acceptable</hi> to his <hi>Patients,</hi> than all his <hi>learning</hi> besides: what does the Physicians great <hi>notional learning</hi> signifie to the Patient, if the medicine be not <hi>improved</hi> and <hi>bettered</hi> by it? 'tis <hi>medicine</hi> that <hi>cures;</hi> and he that gains the <hi>best</hi> medicines shall do the <hi>greatest</hi> cures, and out do all <hi>other</hi> learning whatsoever: and therefore a fore-named <hi>Author,</hi> very discreetly incouraging Physicians to the <hi>preparation</hi> of their Medicines, saith; <hi>When judicious Physicians come to be more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly</hi>
               <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Jonath. Goddards <hi>discourse,</hi> &amp;c. pag. 35.</note>
               <hi>acquainted with the materials of medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and also to experiment and observe operations and processes upon them; especially the more accurate and artificial, as in Chymical Preparations; they will discover the most advantagious ways of prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the most rational proporations in order to composition; and come to contrive and invent new medicaments, exceeding others in their kinds, and improve, beyond what they can imagine of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:42923:46"/> before they have entred this way, and what they can ever otherwise attain; as some learned and ingenious Physicians have done. Nor can it be denyed, that in this course, some Empiricks have stumbled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on very considerable and effectual medicaments, wherewith in some particular cases they have out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done learned Physicians; and by the advantage of making their own medicaments, they bear up and will do, till they be out done in the same kind by such Physician.</hi> Now if <hi>Empiricks</hi> sometimes can out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do <hi>learned</hi> Physicians, by a <hi>rude</hi> tractation of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients, wanting <hi>Philosophical</hi> helps to guide and lead them in their <hi>invention</hi> and <hi>facture</hi> of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines; what then may not a <hi>learned Physician</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly qualified do, when he comes to operate, assisted by the best rules of <hi>Art?</hi> and what great improvements may we not expect in medicines, when all the <hi>learned Professors</hi> shall set upon this work? till then the Practice of Physick (<hi>generally</hi>) will be but mean and common; Physicians <hi>too often</hi> and shamefully <hi>baffled</hi> with Diseases, and <hi>great cures</hi> very scarce.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Advan∣tage. </seg>6</label>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> That he may <hi>preserve</hi> the <hi>Arcana's</hi> of his Art from being <hi>prophaned;</hi> and be <hi>absolute Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> of his own <hi>labours</hi> and <hi>secrets,</hi> secure from any pilfering or undermining person. The <hi>Professors</hi> then will be in a good capacity to <hi>oblige</hi> and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie each other in the <hi>communication</hi> of secrets: or after death to bequeath to some next <hi>Relation,</hi> that in duty he is bound to provide for; and perhaps may stand in <hi>need</hi> of such a help: So that having thus the <hi>free disposal,</hi> the compleat and full benefit of his <hi>labour,</hi> that no pains can be <hi>lost</hi> or <hi>alienated</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:42923:46"/> from him; this cannot but be a great <hi>incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and spur to <hi>industry,</hi> and every ingenious Professor will then exert his power <hi>strenuously,</hi> and be very diligent in operations, to make himself <hi>Mister</hi> of something that's rare and <hi>egregiously</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent. What incouragement is there? and who will labour hard to find out an <hi>excellent secret,</hi> that upon the use thereof, another shall <hi>rob</hi> him of it? I think there are few so good natur'd, that will take any extraordinary pains, to furnish an <hi>Apothecary</hi> with <hi>such</hi> medicines; and therefore it may be a wonder, when any but <hi>common</hi> medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines come to their files: and this is one main rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son why Physicians do not take pains to improve medicines as they <hi>might</hi> and <hi>could</hi> do, but content themselves with common <hi>traditional</hi> medicines, and jog on daily in the same beaten road.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Advan∣tage. </seg>7</label>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> That he may <hi>secure</hi> his own <hi>reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and not expose it to the mercy of others; who either for saving <hi>cost,</hi> sparing <hi>pains,</hi> want of <hi>skill, care,</hi> and <hi>diligence,</hi> in making his Prescripts <hi>exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> (as one of these too often falls out) may render him <hi>unfortunate,</hi> and <hi>defeat</hi> him in <hi>success:</hi> and therefore says a <hi>Doctor</hi> before mentioned, as yet <hi>intangled</hi> in the prescribing mode, but very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably upon <hi>deserting</hi> it, says; <hi>Our Patients lives</hi>
               <note place="margin">D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> C. T. his Answer to a Letter &amp;c. p. 18.</note>
               <hi>and our credits, are too often in the power of an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant confident Fool, or an idle careless Boy.</hi> Since then the <hi>reputation</hi> of a Physician is daily <hi>hazarded,</hi> and lies <hi>lyable</hi> to pay for the <hi>miscarriages</hi> of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines (although the fault be anothers) it behoves him then to have an <hi>especial</hi> care and <hi>regard</hi> to the medicine, and manage this business <hi>himself;</hi>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:42923:47"/> which puts him out of <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>doubt</hi> of any such <hi>casualties</hi> or <hi>abuse</hi> of medicines, and then he will practice with great <hi>confidence</hi> and <hi>boldness;</hi> hoping his <hi>success</hi> will be answerable to his <hi>labour</hi> and <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours,</hi> and the <hi>excellency</hi> of his medicines.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Advan∣tage. </seg>8</label>
               <hi>Eightly,</hi> Physicians being <hi>compleatly furnished</hi> with medicines for all <hi>emergent</hi> occasions, and <hi>free</hi> for all to resort thither; they will be reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for this laudable and industrious undertaking, by a <hi>full employment:</hi> for such people of the <hi>lower rank,</hi> who apply now to <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> and <hi>Quacks</hi> for cheapness (as they suppose) will then more willingly resort to <hi>able Physitians</hi> for their good medicines, when they may have them at a <hi>reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable price,</hi> and therewith the Doctors <hi>advice</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>fee.</hi> Which a Phisician may well do, and with as much ease to himself, as talk over <hi>an urinall</hi> for a <hi>groat.</hi> None then (I think) that have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reason, will decline an able Physicians <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel,</hi> with the <hi>choicest medicines</hi> he can provide for his own Practice; to go to a <hi>Shop,</hi> or any <hi>Empi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> for their <hi>common sale medicines;</hi> when they may have the <hi>one</hi> as cheap as the <hi>other;</hi> and much <hi>cheaper,</hi> if they compare the <hi>goodness</hi> of the one with the other, and what is likely to be the <hi>result</hi> of each: for if you trifle every day with a twelve penny <hi>sophisticate medicine,</hi> or not well <hi>designed,</hi> and effect little or nothing (perhaps <hi>mischief</hi>) and you <hi>linger</hi> on under your infirmities; you cannot say this is a <hi>cheap</hi> saving course, but <hi>expensive</hi> in <hi>time</hi> and <hi>money.</hi> When people shall be made <hi>sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible</hi> of this, they will not be so fond of an <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries Shop,</hi> nor foolishly hearken after every
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:42923:47"/> cheating <hi>Empirick,</hi> that pretends to Physick; but apply generally to the honest and able Physician: whose <hi>reputation</hi> is an ingagement sufficient to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure them of <hi>faithful</hi> and <hi>just</hi> dealing, at a <hi>cheaper</hi> rate than any of these can <hi>really</hi> perform, what ever they may <hi>promise</hi> or <hi>pretend,</hi> to draw you in.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Advan∣tage. </seg>9</label>
               <hi>Ninthly,</hi> This <hi>full</hi> employment will beget a <hi>full increase</hi> of knowledge, in all kinds of diseases; and then the Physician shall have <hi>plentiful</hi> satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in the <hi>frequent</hi> and <hi>full</hi> tryals of his medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines: and his daily <hi>observations</hi> of them in their operations and successes upon several bodies will enable him thereby to replenish his store <hi>succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sively,</hi> with medicines of the <hi>same</hi> design, but of <hi>greater</hi> improvement, and meliorated to a <hi>higher</hi> gradation: whereby (and the only way) <hi>Physick</hi> in a short time will rise to a <hi>high pitch</hi> of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to the great satisfaction and applause of all people: but as yet, and 'tis the unhappiness of this Age, that many ingenious and hopeful Physicians are stopt in their improvements; and their parts likely to decay and wither, for want of incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a good employment to exercise and increase their endowments, and shew their abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of acquirement: But alas, what for <hi>practising Apothecaries,</hi> and all sorts of <hi>Quacks</hi> that are shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully permitted every where; the <hi>legitimate</hi> Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian is sadly <hi>rob'd</hi> of his Practice, <hi>that</hi> which should improve and incourage him: and this is not only an injury to the <hi>Professors,</hi> but much redounds to the prejudice of all <hi>people,</hi> if they rightly knew their own <hi>interest;</hi> which is to <hi>maintain</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage</hi> the learned <hi>industrious</hi> Physician, who on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:42923:48"/> is in a true capacity, and able to serve them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Advan∣tage. </seg>10</label>
               <hi>Tenthly,</hi> Physicians practising with their <hi>own</hi> shall have good opportunities, and be in a better capacity to be <hi>charitable:</hi> First, to such as are very <hi>indigent,</hi> and have no money to bestow for their relief: Secondly, to such who can go no <hi>higher</hi> than barely to <hi>satisfie</hi> what their medicines <hi>cost:</hi> and this a Physician may freely and cordially do, being accommodated with good medicines, and <hi>animated</hi> to good works, by an incouraging <hi>full</hi> employment that may <hi>enable</hi> him to be <hi>generous</hi> and <hi>bountiful,</hi> doing good to all conditions of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for <hi>God</hi>'s sake, as well as for his <hi>own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having now given you a fair prospect of the <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient industrious</hi> practice of Physicians; and exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited plainly to your view, the <hi>benefits</hi> and <hi>advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages</hi> arising thence, and pressing forwards the <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance</hi> and <hi>promotion</hi> of this <hi>Science;</hi> as also that the interest of <hi>Patient</hi> and <hi>Physician</hi> rests there, as most secure: I come now to present you with the <hi>new mode</hi> of <hi>prescribing</hi> to <hi>Apothecaries:</hi> and here take notice, that what hath been said of the good <hi>old</hi> Practice, to justifie and commend that; does also by reflection <hi>condemn</hi> and <hi>disapprove</hi> this <hi>lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> and that manifestly upon the <hi>syncrisis</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison with each other: So that I need not say ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much more, to set forth the unavoidable injuries that result from this deputing of Tradesmen, as Physicians substitutes, to <hi>over-see</hi> and prepare me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines according to their <hi>prescripts:</hi> Yet to make the discovery more compleat and perspicuous, and to shew you the manifest <hi>imprudency</hi> of this <hi>latter</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, and how <hi>insufferable</hi> it is in the <hi>continua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:42923:48"/> observe with me strictly, what this <hi>new</hi> Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice is, and you will see the <hi>fraudulent</hi> garb that is put upon it to render it specious, as also the <hi>empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> and <hi>deceit</hi> that is couched under it.</p>
            <p>This <hi>new mode</hi> of Practice is, to draw and frame medicines upon a <hi>piece</hi> of <hi>Paper;</hi> modelling them into <hi>several</hi> forms, and contriving them for <hi>seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> purposes; varying <hi>pro re nata,</hi> for every <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament</hi> and <hi>case,</hi> by <hi>substracting</hi> and <hi>adding</hi> this and that variously, as the Prescriber <hi>fansies,</hi> or an Author shall <hi>dictate</hi> to him, if he have time to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult his Books. And <hi>here</hi> the Doctor ends his work, and resigns it up into <hi>other</hi> hands to be <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected:</hi> this <hi>draught</hi> or <hi>scheme</hi> of medicine, is to be transmitted to some <hi>Apothecary</hi> to be made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that <hi>platform</hi> and <hi>invention.</hi> And this is thought (by those who are <hi>blinded</hi> with the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy) that it is a <hi>learned</hi> designing of medicines; an <hi>artificial</hi> contrivement; an <hi>exact</hi> appropriation to person and case; a <hi>regular</hi> and <hi>rational</hi> method; a <hi>good</hi> invention to satisfie the people; a <hi>safe</hi> way to trust their lives in; practised by men of <hi>eminent</hi> fame and learning; to whom the <hi>greatest</hi> persons apply for help and relief; and therefore it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by all, that this must needs be the <hi>best</hi> and most <hi>excellent</hi> way of practice.</p>
            <p>But to counter this general &amp; <hi>erroneous approbation,</hi> and oppose this <hi>fond</hi> opinion of <hi>unwary trapt</hi> people; I shall give you my judgment in a direct <hi>Antithesis</hi> and <hi>contradictory</hi> determination. This novel pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice though generally applauded and approved, is not truly <hi>bottomed</hi> and <hi>founded</hi> upon the right learning: for the <hi>basis</hi> of Pharmacy is <hi>experimental
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:42923:49"/> Philosophy,</hi> a certain guide; not <hi>fallacious Book</hi> learning and deceitful <hi>probability. Secondly,</hi> the designment of such medicines are not <hi>artificial,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>latest</hi> and <hi>best</hi> inventions, from cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain tryals of experienced operators in Pharmacy, witness their <hi>Bills</hi> upon the Files. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Their adaptations <hi>pro re nata,</hi> are imaginary, uncertain, and a shooting at <hi>random,</hi> instead of aiming at a <hi>mark;</hi> since no <hi>individual</hi> propriety of body, nor no <hi>new</hi> conjunction and association of medicinal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients are fore-known, but <hi>tryal</hi> makes the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, and begets a <hi>post</hi> knowledge; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore established tryals, well proved, repeated and meliorated medicines, far exceed these conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral new coin'd medicines. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> This pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing mode is an <hi>irrational</hi> course to <hi>fathom</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a very <hi>unlikely</hi> way to improve a natural <hi>Philosopher,</hi> and <hi>impossible</hi> that hereby he should be knowing and skilful in the <hi>various proprieties</hi> of medicinal ingredients. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> 'Tis an excellent invention to satisfie and <hi>indulge</hi> a Physician, that is content to live in <hi>ease</hi> and <hi>ignorance. Sixthly,</hi> A hazardous way to trust peoples <hi>lives</hi> in. <hi>Seventh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> Practised by men as apparently <hi>erroneous</hi> in cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; as <hi>eminent</hi> in fame and learning: whose Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients although the <hi>greatest,</hi> may not be the <hi>wisest</hi> and most judicious; I am sure, not the most <hi>critical</hi> and discerning in this matter, nor such as have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to be rightly informed herein.</p>
            <p>To back these <hi>assertions</hi> (though much hereof is proved in the preceding discourse) and that I may not be thought a <hi>traducer</hi> of this <hi>famed</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and men of great repute exercising therein;
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:42923:49"/> I shall offer farther, to <hi>illustrate</hi> these truths, and <hi>vindicate</hi> them from all <hi>suspition</hi> of calumny: and this I shall do by bringing the <hi>prescribing Doctor</hi> to the <hi>touch-stone,</hi> whereby you may clearly <hi>judge</hi> of this mans abilities, in <hi>designing</hi> and <hi>appointing</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines for the sick (let his parts and learning other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise be ever so good) and whether he be such an <hi>able safe</hi> man in curing, as the world hath <hi>vainly</hi> supposed: the tryal is this. He that is <hi>knowing</hi> and <hi>skilful</hi> in the <hi>forming, adapting,</hi> and <hi>appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of medicines; that is able to <hi>direct</hi> and <hi>correct</hi> medicinal preparations <hi>judiciously,</hi> as a <hi>Master</hi> in this Art; is well acquainted with the <hi>materia me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dica;</hi> in their <hi>genuine,</hi> and <hi>simple, artificial</hi> and <hi>compound</hi> state; and hath ascended these four <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations</hi> of <hi>Pharmaceutic</hi> knowledge. The first <hi>step</hi> he takes, is only a <hi>superficial acquaintance</hi> with the <hi>materia medica;</hi> to know the <hi>face</hi> and <hi>figure</hi> of all natural bodies, especially the more <hi>usual</hi> in medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, rightly to distinguish them by <hi>name</hi> one from another; and not to know them <hi>thus,</hi> is as <hi>absurd</hi> an ignorance, as for a Carpenter not to know <hi>Oak</hi> from <hi>Elm,</hi> and <hi>Beech</hi> from <hi>Firwood.</hi> Can that Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sician be said to be a <hi>natural Philosopher,</hi> that does not so much as know the outside of nature? His <hi>second degree</hi> and progress in knowledge, is to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand the <hi>various</hi> differences in point of <hi>goodness,</hi> that he may make a good <hi>election</hi> of every ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent he appoints for medicine, which is of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance in curing: and not to know <hi>good</hi> from <hi>bad,</hi> is a deficiency next the not knowing <hi>one</hi> kind from <hi>another.</hi> The <hi>third</hi> gradation, is to know the distinct <hi>times</hi> for <hi>storing,</hi> and <hi>different ways</hi> of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:42923:50"/> keeping, proper, and befitting these several <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes;</hi> as also to correct and prepare every thing <hi>duely</hi> in order to compound medicines; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out such <hi>provision,</hi> and <hi>previous</hi> observations in <hi>Pharmacy</hi> (gained by practice and experience) a good medicine cannot be made. The <hi>fourth</hi> gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and compleatment of a Physician in <hi>Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy,</hi> consists of many parts: as first, To make <hi>sutable associations</hi> of ingredients, with their faces looking one way, and conspiring to the <hi>same</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. <hi>Secondly,</hi> To know the <hi>due proportions</hi> of each ingredient, suting with the <hi>form</hi> and <hi>consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stence</hi> of every medicine, as also for a due qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>odors, sapors, &amp;c.</hi> or what else may commend and make a medicine more grateful to the Patient. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To be dextrous and skilful in the <hi>different</hi> artificial ways of <hi>extracting</hi> or <hi>separating</hi> the <hi>vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues</hi> or virtuous parts of several bodies, to elect <hi>this,</hi> and reject <hi>that,</hi> to serve such a purpose. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> To be expert in the <hi>various</hi> ways of <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position</hi> and <hi>union</hi> by fit <hi>mediums;</hi> for as much as, some bodies refuse the <hi>intimate</hi> society and <hi>embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of others, unless by <hi>artificial conjunction</hi> they be reconciled. Fifthly, To know the variety of <hi>menstruums</hi> proper to act upon several bodies, for <hi>extraction</hi> and <hi>dissolution;</hi> for that <hi>penetration</hi> and <hi>retexture</hi> are not wrought <hi>promiscuously,</hi> but by <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that</hi> specially. <hi>Sixthly,</hi> To discern what will <hi>yield</hi> to and <hi>comply</hi> with such a <hi>preparation</hi> and <hi>form</hi> of medicine, and what not. <hi>Seventhly,</hi> To know what are <hi>hostile</hi> and do <hi>destroy</hi> each other, if they be <hi>compounded</hi> together, and what does <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt</hi> or depress each other, within their <hi>sphere</hi> of action. <hi>Eighthly,</hi> To know the various <hi>results</hi> of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:42923:50"/> different <hi>mixtures,</hi> which oftentimes are not to be <hi>imagined,</hi> nor can ever be <hi>thought</hi> of, but are found out by <hi>tryals</hi> and <hi>experiments</hi> of associating and commixing <hi>this</hi> with <hi>that;</hi> and no man can certainly tell the <hi>effects</hi> of any <hi>composition</hi> before the <hi>tryal,</hi> but by <hi>guess</hi> and at a <hi>venture,</hi> which oft proves not so as intended, but much otherwise: and this the <hi>Pharmacopoeian</hi> Physician and <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Philosopher</hi> will fully attest. I might have given some <hi>instances</hi> and <hi>examples</hi> in these parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, but I must contract my self to bring this <hi>discourse</hi> within the <hi>compass</hi> of these sheets.</p>
            <p>Now if you examine the <hi>prescribing Doctor</hi> (that trusts wholly to <hi>Apothecaries</hi> for the making of his medicines) and search into his <hi>abilities</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatness in these four <hi>gradations</hi> of requisite know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, you will find him very <hi>deficient</hi> herein: and I think there is none (<hi>quatenus Prescriber</hi>) will have the face to own himself <hi>Master</hi> of such a <hi>stock</hi> of knowledge; but if any such there be, <hi>reason</hi> will tell you, he is endowed with more <hi>absurd ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rational</hi> confidence, than <hi>truth</hi> in that <hi>assumption:</hi> for as much as these four <hi>gradations</hi> of knowledge are acquired by a <hi>practical experience</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with all the ingredients and their seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral preparations in the <hi>Pharmaceutic Art,</hi> by <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spection, tractation,</hi> and <hi>operation,</hi> and not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise. Therefore a meer <hi>notional</hi> man, a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scriber,</hi> a <hi>Book</hi> Physician, that draws all his skill out of his <hi>Library,</hi> is much <hi>estranged</hi> from this certain compleat knowledge: and at <hi>best,</hi> in what he seems to know from <hi>tradition,</hi> he is but an <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturer</hi> thereon, a man of <hi>fortune</hi> and <hi>chance;</hi> he takes all upon <hi>trust;</hi> and he may as likely (and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:42923:51"/> very often he does, witness his <hi>Bills</hi> upon the <hi>file</hi>) depend upon an <hi>error,</hi> and embrace <hi>falshood</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of <hi>truth;</hi> nor shall he ever be informed by <hi>prescribing</hi> to <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> but persist in his false <hi>imaginations</hi> and presumptions; for <hi>operating</hi> and <hi>experimenting</hi> in the Laboratory, is that which <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms, proves,</hi> and <hi>settles</hi> a true judgment in medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, which poring in the <hi>library,</hi> shall never do, although he be a studious man all his life time. Let none then think to justifie himself, because of his great learning otherwise; for admit that, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deficient and inexpert in this most requisite part of learning; he is (assuredly) very insufficient and an unsafe Practiser. Whoever therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented <hi>prescribing,</hi> as a mode and custom for Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians to follow, seducing them from the <hi>first esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishment,</hi> and most rational endeavours in the <hi>preparation</hi> of medicines; were the <hi>greatest</hi> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the <hi>progress</hi> of this Science, to the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and advance of the <hi>Professors,</hi> and hath proved most <hi>pernicious</hi> to the Sick. The consideration whereof made <hi>Chr. Langius</hi> complain; <hi>Sed hoc sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chr. Lang. curios. med. pag. 146.</note>
               <hi>silentio non transmittendum existimamus; pessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè illos de bono publico meritos, qui primi hanc sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me arduam arma medica conficiendi disciplinam a medicina avulserunt, &amp; servis suis unice commise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, &amp;c.</hi> Notwithstanding our just complaints of the great <hi>abuses</hi> daily offered to our <hi>Profession,</hi> by men unreasonably introduced as <hi>appertainers</hi> to this Science; their <hi>invading</hi> our rights, and boldly <hi>usurping</hi> the medical Practice; <hi>prostituting</hi> the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of this Art for <hi>gain,</hi> and many other insuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable inconveniencies relating both to <hi>Patient</hi> and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:42923:51"/>
               <hi>Physician;</hi> yet this unhappy invention of <hi>prescrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> or the ridiculous custom of Physicians making medicines with <hi>Pen</hi> and <hi>Ink,</hi> is most injuriously promoted and continued; and few there are that seriously consider the mischief they have done, by <hi>complying</hi> with, and <hi>upholding</hi> this <hi>male-practice,</hi> I shall therefore search farther into this imprudent innovation, and let you see the <hi>vanity</hi> and empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of this prescribing Practice, so <hi>fondly</hi> esteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the people, and unworthily kept up by the Professors; and that I shall do by examining the <hi>basis</hi> thereof, if it be <hi>firm</hi> and <hi>solid;</hi> whether the Practice of Physick may rest upon it, as <hi>secure, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional,</hi> and <hi>justifiable;</hi> or whether it be not an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, ignorant,</hi> and <hi>dangerous</hi> Practice; not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming a <hi>Philosopher,</hi> nor answering that <hi>trust</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posited in the <hi>Professors,</hi> being of such weight and moment, wherein the <hi>lives</hi> of all people are most neerly concerned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First</hi> then, either this <hi>prescribing</hi> or the <hi>Prescripts</hi> of an Apothecary Doctor, are founded upon <hi>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> and taken up upon <hi>trust</hi> from Authors; or <hi>secondly,</hi> they are grounded upon some former <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riclitations</hi> and successful <hi>adventures</hi> of their own in parallel cases. Or <hi>thirdly,</hi> they are designed and composed <hi>theorically</hi> and <hi>conjecturally</hi> contriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, upon <hi>probability</hi> and <hi>reason,</hi> drawn from the common reputed single nature of the <hi>ingredients,</hi> selected and appropriated to a <hi>special</hi> case, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into such a form of medicine, most sutable to that purpose. Now in all these three <hi>prescripts</hi> variously and severally bottomed (and I think the <hi>enumeration</hi> compriseth the <hi>generical</hi> latitude) the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:42923:52"/>
               <hi>prescribing</hi> Physician is justly to be taxed, and may be reputed an <hi>uncertain, unsafe</hi> Practiser, or a <hi>hazardous</hi> Undertaker of the Sick, let him be ever so learned and well accomplisht otherwise; as plainly appears upon the particular examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of these three <hi>prescripts</hi> differently grounded and presumed.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>first,</hi> if your judgment depends upon the supposed <hi>skill</hi> and credit of an <hi>Author,</hi> or a <hi>Book</hi>-guide in the <hi>election</hi> and composition of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines; then 'tis not <hi>you</hi> (if it take effect) that cures, but your <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>monitor,</hi> and your good fortune to consult <hi>him</hi> and not <hi>another;</hi> you practice by his repute, by his supposed ability and experience, not by your <hi>own;</hi> not by your <hi>own</hi> reason grounded upon <hi>experience</hi> and <hi>practical</hi> knowledge in medicinal <hi>preparations</hi> and tryals: but depending upon <hi>this</hi> and <hi>that</hi> learned man, you appoint <hi>this</hi> and <hi>that</hi> medicine of his commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and so the good women practice by their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt Book. That this is <hi>warrantable</hi> and <hi>safe,</hi> is most reasonably denyed: <hi>First,</hi> because Authors do often <hi>transcribe</hi> from one another, and take up upon <hi>trust,</hi> as you <hi>Prescribers</hi> do: and 'tis very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain who <hi>proved</hi> and <hi>tryed</hi> this or that medicine sufficiently, and made true observations thereon: some perhaps never made them <hi>otherwise</hi> than a fair <hi>draught</hi> upon a piece of Paper, as you your selves use to do. <hi>Secondly,</hi> because medicines in former times were not so well contrived, <hi>safe, artificial,</hi> and <hi>compleat,</hi> in their <hi>first</hi> and <hi>rough</hi> inventions, as now in these later days; and the <hi>Ancients</hi> knew not those excellent ways of <hi>correcting</hi> and <hi>preparing,</hi>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:42923:52"/> as by long and often experience is discovered gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually to diligent and inquisitive <hi>Operators</hi> of this later industrious Age: therefore <hi>those</hi> are not <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplars</hi> for any to imitate and transcribe; but to <hi>prove, operate</hi> upon, and <hi>meliorate</hi> in the <hi>Laboratory. Thirdly,</hi> because many <hi>frivolous, inefficacious,</hi> and <hi>bad</hi> medicines, are scattered frequently here and there in <hi>Authors</hi> of great learning and fame, and commended to posterity (with many other great <hi>errors</hi>) which deserve and ought to be <hi>rased</hi> out; and not to stand as <hi>Copies</hi> for other men to write after: which <hi>patterns</hi> have shamed <hi>great</hi> Physicians their followers (who else had been <hi>good</hi> Physicians) and frustrated their expectations, with the <hi>loss</hi> of their Patients <hi>lives,</hi> and the <hi>vilifying</hi> of this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Art:</hi> and of such sort, I can point you out enough for proof. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> because Prescribers have not that discerning judgment in the choice of medicines (proved <hi>pag.</hi> 14, 15, 16, 17. being <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practised</hi> and <hi>unskilful</hi> in their preparations) but chop upon medicines from their high <hi>commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> and are biassed by the false <hi>eulogies</hi> commonly attending them, not directed and determined to this or that by a <hi>judicious election.</hi> Wherefore the <hi>reliance</hi> that these men have upon <hi>Authors</hi> in the choice of medicines is <hi>deceitful,</hi> and their Practice <hi>hazardous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the second, that is just the <hi>Empirick</hi>'s Practice; and his confidence in the use of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, does arise after the same manner, from some fortunate blind experiments, and good luck in curing: not from the true reasons of the medicine, collated with the nature of the disease: not from
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:42923:53"/> any just and full account he is able to give of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micable congruity of the associated ingredients, or their conspiring natures to the same intention; their due proportions, the exquisitness and fitness of each particular previous preparation; nor from the rational and artificial designment and adapta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole by a certain knowledge and true observations in <hi>Pharmaceutic</hi> experiments (this only an expert <hi>Pharmacopoeian</hi> Doctor is able to do, proved <hi>pag.</hi> 14, 15, 16, 17. also 81, 82,) but relying upon some former good success super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening the medicine in like case, gives him incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to repeat the same.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>third,</hi> that seems to be a grave <hi>learned</hi> Plot, and a <hi>secure</hi> design in curing, is the most <hi>hazardous</hi> adventure, and most <hi>dangerous</hi> of the three: for here you set upon the Sick with an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, untryed, new medicine,</hi> which what it will prove, a more <hi>skilful</hi> man than you cannot tell; for those expert <hi>Physicians</hi> that prepare medicines for their own practice, that are very <hi>conversant</hi> and well <hi>experienced</hi> in various medicinal preparations (far beyond your <hi>notional conjectural</hi> knowledge in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing) I must summon them in for their <hi>testimony</hi> and confirmation; that they are not satisfied in, nor have tryed any new medicine <hi>sufficiently</hi> to esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish it in their number of well <hi>approved</hi> medicines, under <hi>six</hi> months time or <hi>longer,</hi> by frequent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, alterations, and several tryals in <hi>use</hi> and <hi>curative</hi> probation. For my own part I have been <hi>revising</hi> and <hi>meliorating</hi> some medicines for many years, by various <hi>alterations</hi> and <hi>tryals,</hi> and yet I am not so fully satisfied as to <hi>acquiesce</hi> and sit
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:42923:53"/> down with what I have acquired. But you (Mr. <hi>Prescriber</hi>) can contrive and <hi>hatch</hi> a new composi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in a quarter of an hour, and give it with as much <hi>confidence,</hi> as if you had been frequently an <hi>elaborator</hi> of this medicine for <hi>seven years.</hi> How come <hi>you</hi> to be such an even <hi>guesser</hi> at medicines, that <hi>never</hi> made any? if you hit it <hi>right,</hi> you are the <hi>luckiest</hi> man in the world: but common <hi>reason</hi> tells me, and your <hi>practice</hi> does declare, that you are more <hi>bold</hi> than <hi>fortunate</hi> herein. No wise man goes to fight, but he first <hi>examines</hi> and <hi>trys</hi> his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, that they may not deceive him; so likewise a prudent and careful Physician, <hi>proves</hi> his <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines</hi> very well before he comes to use them in good earnest; especially in <hi>acute</hi> Diseases, that allow no time to <hi>delay</hi> or <hi>dally</hi> in: here one <hi>error,</hi> or one bad <hi>medicine,</hi> is enough to march off the Patient: this is not a time to practice with <hi>hap hazard</hi> medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, by new <hi>appropriations</hi> as you may fancy; but you must rely upon <hi>standing</hi> medicines, well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimented and reformed by several <hi>tryals;</hi> and in these are the greatest safety of the Patients <hi>life,</hi> and the Physicians <hi>reputation:</hi> these will not <hi>boggle</hi> and play <hi>jadish</hi> tricks with you, as the new <hi>untry'd</hi> medicines, that most commonly shame their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster: and therefore the <hi>person</hi> and <hi>case</hi> ought to be deliberately chosen for such <hi>new</hi> experiments, and the medicine well inspected in the <hi>preparation;</hi> else no <hi>true</hi> observation can be remarked thence. To press home the <hi>absurdness</hi> and <hi>uncertainty</hi> of this practice; he that is not <hi>practically</hi> and <hi>experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally</hi> acquainted by tractation and tryals in the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boratory,</hi> with every <hi>single</hi> ingredient, he adds to
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:42923:54"/> his medicine, puts he knows not what together: and he that is well acquainted with the nature of each <hi>single,</hi> does not yet certainly know what the <hi>result</hi> will be in the <hi>compound</hi> until the <hi>tryal:</hi> as the ingredients of <hi>Gunpowder</hi> or <hi>Aurum fulminans,</hi> have no such furious effects in their <hi>single</hi> natures; but being so <hi>prepared</hi> and <hi>compounded,</hi> they have a strange force and power: and likewise many other <hi>compounds</hi> and <hi>mixtures</hi> that might be instanced, far different in their <hi>result,</hi> from each <hi>single</hi> nature. A <hi>Prescriber</hi> or <hi>Speculator</hi> in medicines, does not consider, nor can he <hi>find</hi> it in his <hi>study,</hi> how the ingredients of medicines are <hi>varied</hi> and <hi>changed,</hi> by the diversity of <hi>preparation</hi> and <hi>conjunction;</hi> how their properties are <hi>intended</hi> or <hi>remitted, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct,</hi> or <hi>advanced,</hi> by adding of <hi>this</hi> or substract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>that;</hi> having <hi>similar</hi> or <hi>dissimilar</hi> and opposite qualities, <hi>emaning</hi> from their different <hi>forms</hi> and <hi>seminalities,</hi> or from artificial <hi>modifications</hi> and <hi>transmutations</hi> in preparation: for these <hi>secrets</hi> are known and discovered only to an expert <hi>operator</hi> by due observations upon various <hi>tryals</hi> and <hi>processes</hi> in the preparation of medicines, and not otherwise: So that from hence, we may very rationally and undoubtedly conclude; that the <hi>designing</hi> and <hi>compounding</hi> of medicines are very <hi>nice</hi> things; not to be contrived in the <hi>study</hi> only, and so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended on; but to be proved also in the <hi>Labora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory</hi> and <hi>warily</hi> approved by use; and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly also, that those <hi>ex tempore</hi> medicines and sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>inventions</hi> of Prescribers, <hi>pro re nata,</hi> are very <hi>uncertain, casual,</hi> and <hi>hazardous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I affirm therefore from these reasons deposited;
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:42923:54"/> to practice with or appoint medicines, as <hi>Prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> do, without a <hi>firm</hi> well <hi>grounded</hi> experience in them, and certain knowledge gained by their frequent <hi>preparation</hi> and <hi>melioration;</hi> is a <hi>slight, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful</hi> Practice: either to relye upon <hi>fallacious tradition,</hi> or their own <hi>blind</hi> casual <hi>successes</hi> and <hi>repetitions;</hi> or to <hi>presume</hi> and <hi>adventure</hi> upon new invented <hi>conjectural</hi> medicines, for the first en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters and onsets, before tryals with <hi>secure ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved</hi> standing medicines, is not warrantable nor safe: and besides all this uncertainty, to refer the <hi>management</hi> and <hi>preparation</hi> of these dubious chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medicines, to the <hi>care, skill,</hi> and <hi>honesty</hi> of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in Physick, and their <hi>servants;</hi> is such an <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumulation</hi> of egregious failings, and a <hi>multiplying</hi> of imprudent irrational <hi>adventures;</hi> as he that would be counted a true <hi>experimental</hi> Philosopher, an <hi>able, steddy,</hi> well grounded Practiser, and a <hi>safe</hi> undertaker of the Sick, must <hi>disown</hi> and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly <hi>reject:</hi> but he that diligently betakes himself to the <hi>ancient</hi> industrious Practice; not trusting to <hi>tradition, speculative</hi> notions, and <hi>substitutes</hi> in Pharmacy; but <hi>personally</hi> acting, inspecting, and remarking all <hi>Pharmaceutic</hi> and other <hi>Philosophical</hi> experiments; may thereby gain a stock of <hi>certain</hi> knowledge to relye on, and acquire <hi>sound</hi> and <hi>real</hi> abilities in curing; he may then settle <hi>true</hi> observations as guides and monitors in the whole Practice of <hi>Pharmacy;</hi> and being sedulously di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sposed in this capacity, he may <hi>confidently</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servingly</hi> hope to obtain the great <hi>Arcana's</hi> of this <hi>Art,</hi> which will enable him to perform <hi>true</hi> service
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:42923:55"/> and administer <hi>great</hi> assistance to the <hi>Sick;</hi> and hereby to purchase most worthy fame and credit to <hi>himself</hi> and his <hi>Profession:</hi> such a man as this, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he only deserves the <hi>character</hi> and <hi>Title,</hi> of an <hi>able, careful,</hi> and <hi>compleat</hi> Physician: but he that seeks after, or pretends to great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and abilities in Curing, not thus qualified and <hi>expert</hi> in medicinal preparations, but puft up with <hi>traditional</hi> notions and <hi>Book</hi> experience; he is an <hi>Impostor</hi> to himself and others: and this is the unhappy case of <hi>prescribing,</hi> or the strange cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom of Physicians making medicines with <hi>Pen</hi> and <hi>Ink.</hi> And here I must take notice (lest I be thought a <hi>stranger</hi> to the matter, and give incouragement of advantage) that there is a sort of men (but a <hi>few</hi>) who although they practice with <hi>Shop Medicines</hi> and common culpable <hi>Recipe's,</hi> like other <hi>Prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers;</hi> yet do operate privately to ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge than the rest, and pretend to higher things; thinking hereby they can make a handsome <hi>Plea,</hi> &amp; evade much of the guilt charged in this Discourse. To such as these I have given a fair <hi>check</hi> in a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <note n="*" place="margin">The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Physick re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived, &amp;c. p. 106. to p. 114.</note>
               <hi>Tract,</hi> appendant to that Treatise entituled, <hi>Vita sana &amp; longa,</hi> whither I must refer the <hi>Reader,</hi> not having room to insert it here: and more I have to say against this jugling device and pretext (used as a <hi>foil</hi> to set off and commend, or <hi>patronise</hi> a spu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious illegitimate Practice) when any such Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor shall stand forth in justification of his integrity, and the warrantable discharge of his Function: I doubt not then, but to <hi>extort</hi> this confession from him: <hi>Video meliora proboque, deteriora sequor;</hi> if he
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:42923:55"/> be not very obstinate to the <hi>convictions</hi> of reason, and <hi>perverse</hi> against the truth.</p>
            <p>I might have enlarged my self upon several <hi>heads,</hi> and in divers <hi>parts</hi> of this Discourse to illustrate and press home the <hi>verity</hi> of our asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: but what hath been delivered is sufficient at this time, until some <hi>party</hi> concerned does ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in their defence, by a sober <hi>ratiocination</hi> and solid <hi>argumentative</hi> answer, not an <hi>invective</hi> taunt, not a <hi>reviling contumelious</hi> return; which notably insinuates and suggests the cause to be <hi>bad</hi> on that side: to desert the <hi>matter</hi> in contest, and fall upon the <hi>person,</hi> squibbing and flirting with a little <hi>frothy</hi> wit to no purpose; strongly argues that business to be <hi>naught,</hi> and will not abide a fair <hi>debate:</hi> but if you will answer me <hi>directly</hi> and <hi>fully</hi> to the particulars charged, without <hi>evasions</hi> and <hi>shifts;</hi> laying aside animosity and <hi>self</hi> interest; contending only for the <hi>truth,</hi> the prosperous <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement</hi> of this Science, the <hi>welfare</hi> of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors, and <hi>safety</hi> of the Sick; your ingenuity herein will mitigate <hi>à tanto</hi> many failings, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to your advantage. I desire no more of you, than such an <hi>ingenuous</hi> management of this <hi>disceptation;</hi> that the world may be satisfied, wherein their interest of <hi>life</hi> and <hi>health consists</hi> and rests most <hi>secure;</hi> and that the <hi>provision</hi> wherewith nature is plentifully stored, for the preservation and relief of infirm man, may most <hi>successfully</hi> and <hi>happily</hi> be dispensed: expecting this candor and clear dealing from you (if your cause will admit of fair play, and an honest <hi>sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere,</hi>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:42923:56"/> argumentation) I shall wait your <hi>Answer:</hi> until then I know not where I am <hi>weak</hi> or <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient,</hi> in this undertaking; or where the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse party will take advantage: but when I come to view their <hi>strength,</hi> and find <hi>how</hi> they will oppose, or <hi>where</hi> they will press upon me; and what <hi>objections</hi> more can be started, than I have here <hi>anticipated:</hi> I shall then exactly know the <hi>scope</hi> and main <hi>points</hi> of this difference; the Adversary's utmost power, and what <hi>more</hi> I have to prove: This contest then will be contracted, and drawn into some small compass. Upon <hi>Reply</hi> (which you may be sure of) I shall then <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inforce</hi> such arguments as may be thought (upon new <hi>sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestions</hi>) not so clearly convincing; and apply so close to any <hi>new matter</hi> of opposition, as I doubt not but to <hi>stifle</hi> the validity of any <hi>Plea, argument,</hi> or <hi>objection,</hi> that shall be offered to our conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as a <hi>bar</hi> to the design and intention of this Discourse.</p>
            <p>If I be thought too <hi>sharp</hi> and <hi>severe</hi> (at first sight) in some parts of this Discourse; (if well consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) I am not <hi>culpable</hi> therein, but to be <hi>excused;</hi> the <hi>urgency</hi> of the Cause <hi>prompts</hi> me to it, and will bear me out; since I plead not my <hi>particular</hi> inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest or <hi>private</hi> quarrel; but a <hi>publick</hi> safety, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Non meam sed medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae, medico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp; aegro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sam ago.</hi>
               </note> concern of great importance, which very grosly hath been <hi>abused:</hi> and therefore not to be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended with too <hi>tender</hi> and <hi>soft</hi> language, which is unlikely to make impression upon some sort of men, being <hi>obdurate, fixed,</hi> and <hi>habituated</hi> in a gainful easie confederate Custom, and combined
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:42923:56"/> interest. What seeming deficiencies have attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this undertaking; I doubt not but the <hi>unbiassed</hi> and <hi>impartial</hi> Reader, will favourably interpret; for the <hi>sincerity</hi> of the <hi>Authors</hi> intention, and the <hi>necessity</hi> of this work to be promoted.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>London <hi>From my house in</hi> Fetter-Lane.</dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:42923:57"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed.</head>
            <q>Morbus Polyrhyzos &amp; Polymorphaeus.</q>
            <p>A Treatise of the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> examining opinions of the most solid and grave Writers, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Nature and Cure of this Disease, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Everard Maynwaring</hi> Doctor in Physick.</p>
            <q>Tabidorum Narratio.</q>
            <p>A Treatise of <hi>Consumptions, Scorbutic Atrophies, Tabes Anglica, Hectic Fevers, Phthises, spermatic</hi> and <hi>venereous</hi> wastings; Radically demonstrating their Nature and Cures, from vital and Morbific Causes.</p>
            <p>By the same Author.</p>
            <q>Medicus Absolutus <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>The <hi>Compleat Physician,</hi> qualified and dignified: The Rise and Progress of Physick, Historically, Chronologically, and Philosophically illustrated. Physicians of different Sects and Judgments, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ractered and distinguished, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the same Author.</p>
            <q>Vita sana &amp; longa.</q>
            <p>The <hi>Preservation of Health,</hi> and <hi>Prolongation of Life;</hi> proposed and proved in the due observance of remarkable precautions, and daily practicable Rules, relating to body and mind, compendiously abstracted from the Institutions and Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>By the same Author.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42923:57"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>